.
S.F. Gov tv san francisco
television
.
>> good afternoon everyone.
Welcome to the FEBRUARY 25th,
2025 regular meeting of the san
francisco board of supervisors
.
>> MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll?
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chen chen present
supervisor chen chen present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
present supervisor engardio and
engardio present supervisor
fielder fielder present
supervisor mahmood mahmood
PRESIDENT Supervisor mandolin
PRESIDENT Mandolin PRESIDENT
Supervisor melgar melgar
present supervisor sadr sadr
present supervisor sherril
sheryl present and supervisor
walton walton present MR.
PRESIDENT all members are
present.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk.
The san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges that
we are on the unceded ancestral
homeland of the rahmatullah
aloni who are the original
inhabitants of the san
francisco peninsula.
As the indigenous stewards of
this land and in accordance
with their traditions the raw
materials saloni have never
ceded lost nor forgotten their
responsibilities as the
caretakers of this place as
well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory.
As guests we recognize that we
benefit from living and working
on their traditional homelands.
We wish to pay our respects by
acknowledge acknowledging the
ancestors, elders and relatives
of the romita aloni community
and by affirming their
sovereign rights as first
peoples.
Colleagues, will you join me
in reciting the pledge of
allegiance?
I pledge allegiance to the flag
of the united states of america
the republic which stands one
nation under GOD indivisible
with liberty and justice for
all.
>> on behalf of our board of
supervisors I want to
acknowledge the staff at S.F.
Gov tv and especially today
jaime echevarria who record
each of our meetings and make
the transcript transcripts
available to the public.
MADAM Clerk, are there any
communications?
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
San francisco board of
supervisors welcomes your
attendance at this meeting
today here in the board's
legislative chamber room 250
within city hall on the second
floor or you MAY also watch the
proceeding on S.F. Gop tv's
channel 26 or view the live
stream at w w w dot S.F. Geo v
tv.Org.
You also can submit your public
comment in writing.
You can use email send it to
boss at as f gov dawg or use
the postal service to the san
francisco board of supervisors
the number one DR. Carlton b
goodlatte place city hall room
244 san francisco california
94102.
And finally if you need to make
a reasonable accommodation
request under the americans
with disabilities act or if you
need language assistance,
please contact the clerk's
office at least two business
days in advance.
Please call (415) 554-5184.
>> thank you.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> let's go to approval of the
meeting minutes.
This is the approval of the
JANUARY 14th, 2025 board
meeting minutes.
>> all right.
Colleagues, are there any
changes to these meeting
minutes?
Seeing none.
Can I have a motion to approve
the minutes as presented moved
by walton and seconded by
sherril.
MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll on the minutes
supervisor mahmood mahmood eyes
supervisor randleman I
mendelson I supervisor melgar
melgar I supervisor sartor
sartor eyes supervisor sherril
sherril eyes supervisor walton
walton eyes supervisor chan
chin eyes supervisor chin chin
eyes supervisor dorsey dorsey
eyes supervisor and engardio
and engardio I and supervisor
fielder fielder I there are 11
eyes thank you MADAM Clerk
without objection the minutes
will be approved after public
comment as presented let's go
to our consent agenda items one
and two items one through two
are on consent.
These items are considered
routine if a member objects an
item MAY be removed and
considered separately.
colleagues does anyone want to
sever any items from the
consent agenda seeing no one
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on items one
through two supervisor mahmood
mahmood eyes supervisor
randleman mandel men eyes
supervisor melgar melgar eyes
supervisor sauder sorter eyes
supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chin eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor and gaudio and
gaudio eye and supervisor
fielder fielder either or 11
eyes without objection these
ordinances are finally passed
MADAM Clerk can you take us to
our regular agenda unfinished
business item three item three
is an ordinance to amend the
planning code to permit the use
of california debt limit
allocation committee tax exempt
bond financing and tax credits
for certain affordable housing
projects that provide
additional affordable units or
deeper affordability levels
than required by the
inclusionary housing ordinance
and to require the mayor's
office of housing and community
development to report on such
projects to amend the health
code to exempt such affordable
housing projects from
compliance with the requirement
that new buildings be construct
and operated and maintained
using alternate water sources
for non-potable uses to affirm
the secret determination and to
make the appropriate findings.
>> all right.
I think we can take this item
same house, same call without
objection this ordinance is
finally passed.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item number four?
>> item four.
This is an ordinance to amend
the administrative code to
modify the waivers of specified
contract related requirements
in the administrative labor and
employment and environment
codes for electricity and
related product transactions to
authorize binding arbitration
and to increase the annual
expenditure limit for energy
procurements from 200 million
to 300 million and the revenue
collection limit from 10
million to 300 million and
we'll take this item same
house, same call without
objection.
This ordinance is passed on
first reading MADAME Clerk, can
you please call item five item
five this resolution approves a
lease terminate an agreement
for the harvey milk terminal
one retail concession lease
eight at the san francisco
international airport between
minute suites travelers retreat
sfo llc as tenant and the city
and we can take this item same
house same call without
objection this resolution is
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item six?
>> item six is a resolution to
approve the specialty retail
minimum annual guarantee rent
reduction program for certain
specialty retail concession
tenants to allow the airport to
do a one time adjustment of the
minimum annual guarantee due
under the leases and changing
the method for future
adjustments of the minimum
annual guarantees.
>> and we'll take this same
house same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item seven?
Item seven this is a resolution
to authorize the department of
technology to enter into a
first amendment to the
enterprise agreement with ssp
data inc to purchase palo alto
software products.
To extend the term for three
years for a new total term JUNE
1st 2023 through MAY 31st 2029
for 40 million and we'll take
this item same house, same call
without objection the
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAME Clerk, can you please
call item eight?
Item eight this is a resolution
that approves and authorizes
the sale to the city of san
bruno approximately 68,000ft2
of real property for 5000 and
to affirm the secret
determination and to make the
appropriate findings and we can
take this item same house, same
call without objection the
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk, please call item
nine.
>> item nine resolution to
authorize the office of the
treasurer and tax collector to
sell at public auction and
sealed bid auction certain
parcels of tax defaulted real
property and we'll take this
item same house, same call.
>> without objection this
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk, please call item
ten.
>> item ten resolution to
approve the ninth amendment to
a contract between the
municipal transportation agency
and tags co llc for services
related to the towing, storage
and disposal of abandoned and
illegally parked vehicles.
To approve a $15.3 million
increase and for a new total
contract amount of 136.7
million the balance of the
second year in the last three
years of the five year
extension with no changes to
the term through MARCH 31st
2026.
Okay.
And we'll take this item same
house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 11?
>> item 11 this is a resolution
to retroactive approve a
contract agreement between the
city of san francisco and the
department of state hospitals
for early access and
stabilization services for a
three year term through
DECEMBER 31st, 2027 and for an
amount of approximately 3.3
million.
>> and we'll take this item the
same house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call our next item item 12 this
is a resolution to
retroactively authorize the
department of public health to
accept and expend an
approximate $829,000 grant from
the department of justice
through the san francisco
general hospital foundation for
a program entitled children and
adolescents support advocacy
and resources through SEPTEMBER
30th, 2026 and will take this
item same house, same call
without objection the
resolutions adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call our next item item 13 this
is a resolution to
retroactively authorize the
mayor's office of housing and
community development to
execute and submit a
certification of acceptance of
allocation requirements to the
california department of social
services and to take all action
in compliance with the
certification to authorize the
city to accept and expend the
$250,000 grant under the
special programs appropriated
through the budget act of 2024
section 195 for the term JULY
first 2024 through JUNE 30th
2027 for the center of
immigrant protection to provide
supportive services and
programing for the immigrant
community in san francisco.
We can take this item same
house, same call.
Without objection the
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call our next item?
>> item 14 was referred without
recommendation from the budget
and finance committee.
It's a resolution to approve
the sixth amendment sixth
amendment to a grant agreement
between the office of economic
and workforce development and
mid-market foundation for the
management of the mid-market
tenderloin community based
safety program to increase the
grant amount by 4 million for a
new total of approximately 69.8
million excuse me that is 68.8
million through JUNE 30th 2025.
>> chair chan thank you present
amendment colleagues and I rise
to speak to why this item was
forwarded out of committee
without recommendation.
I think many of you already
know that in the past that to
up to date the city is still
facing a looming budget deficit
of $1 billion layer on top of
that even a greater challenge
that in a prior fiscal year
with now we have the trump
administration injecting
greater chaos and uncertainty
into our state and local
budgets.
We already spent more than $68
million on this contract since
2018 without clear result and
matrix for success.
And now for this fiscal year
alone with this amendment
additional $4 million we will
have spent about $25 million
in this fiscal year just for
this contract alone.
In this one year I want to give
you sort of a context of what
that means.
>> the same $25 million is also
approximately the same amount
that that mayor breed has held
up for this very same fiscal
year.
And these including funding for
dental care and health care at
our public school sites.
And in fact supervisor souder
has a resolution for us to vote
on later today is to make sure
that we have celebrate and
recognize children.
Dental health care day or in.
And so with that also the very
same $25 million our
transitional age youth
outpatient rates and behavioral
health support workforce
development women and victim
services tenants counseling
services, rental subsidies,
violence interventions services
and a 24 hour pit stop program
which you know that in the
mission and many other
neighborhoods really, really
need.
So knowing that there are a lot
of people and services are
competing for the very same $25
million that this contract
represents, I want to
articulate why I will be voting
against this contract amendment
today.
How do we deliver equity or
equitable city services in this
coming year is is something
that we need to start talking
about right now not until JUNE
.
>> we should know that a dollar
is a dollar a dollar spent on
one thing is a dollar missing
for another city services that
we now have to identify another
dollar or worse that we now
have to cut and reduce.
I wish we're not where we're at
today that I can actually say
let's move forward with all the
dollars that we needed to
support everything that need
our support when it comes to
city services and
neighborhoods.
But it is one of those moments
that we have to face the
financial reality I leave to
you colleagues I am not here to
urging you to support or
against this contract.
I am here to simply remind you
as your budget committee chair
that when we spend this money
it's actually being taking out
from somewhere else.
It's a tradeoff conversation
that we must make and but today
I am going to be voting against
this very $4 million additional
$4 million for this contract
being aware that it's coming
from somewhere else including
the list I just provided to
you.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Chair and supervisor mahmud.
>> colleagues, I'd like to
speak out in support of this
item which is requesting an
increase of grant funding for
community based safety programs
to JUNE 30th, 20 25.
>> I think all of us can agree
it would be an understatement
to say these programs have been
critical for the neighborhoods
in district five especially
in the tenderloin as well as
in district six and so and so
MAY as well if you walked into
work today and walked through
U.N. Plaza or grabbed a coffee
at phil's and golden gate, you
were likely greeted with a warm
good morning and have a lovely
rest of your day by someone
smiling in a vest whose work is
funded by this grant.
These kind words that brighten
your morning are just a small
part of the work done by
community ambassadors who do so
much of the important work our
city departments cannot do.
And I have heard repeatedly
from S.F. Pd that this is work
that they cannot do.
>> these are men and women who
were once incarcerated but have
been given a second chance at
life, a second chance at being
part of our community and who
possess a unique life
experience which allows them to
connect with others who are
struggling in our streets from
addiction, homelessness, mental
health issues or a combination
of the three.
These ambassador programs at
this money will fund where
deployed have been shown to
reduce crime in areas by as
much as 52% and drug crimes by
80%.
As a tenderloin resident I know
I appreciate seeing them in my
neighborhood and but I've heard
from neighbors who reached out
on this particular item
extremely concerned about what
might happen next if they were
cut because community
ambassadors have become just
that a part of our community.
I've heard from S.F. Pd and dpw
how instrumental these
community ambassadors are for
complimenting their work, not
replacing it to keep our
streets safe and clean.
At the same time I hear my
colleague's concerns about the
need to review contracting for
accountability and for change.
And I'm looking forward to
going through that process
during this budget cycle.
But we need to make sure that
any replacement or anything
that happens is done in a way
that doesn't result in an
immediate reduction of service
that would have disastrous
effects for the neighborhoods
that have seen that double
digit reduction in crime and
drug dealing where these
ambassadors are placed in the
interim this program is driving
positive results and if we are
to make changes we need to do
it in a regulated fashion that
we have something to replace
over time.
>> but overall these are
positive results for our
residents that you simply
cannot put a price on community
massive programs like those
funded in mid-market and
tenderloin make our streets
safer for families and children
who live here and for those on
transit commuting to work and
for those visiting us from far
away to take in to our great
city.
So I urge my colleagues to vote
in support of this item.
Thank you.
Supervisor mahmud.
MADAM Clerk, could you please
call the roll on this item on
item 14.
>> supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor mandolin.
All right.
Mendelssohn I supervisor melgar
I melgar I supervisor sadr sadr
I supervisor sherril sherrell I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chin chin no
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and gaudio and
gaudio I and supervisor fielder
fielder I there are ten eyes
and one no with supervisor chan
voting no.
>> all right without objection
this resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, could you
please call item 15?
>> item 15 this is an ordinance
to amend the planning code to
exempt certain types of
projects in the downtown area
that replace nonresidential
uses with residential uses from
development impact fees and
requirements to include the
inclusionary housing fee.
Remove the application deadline
from the commercial to
residential adaptive reuse
program and to require periodic
reporting to the inclusionary
housing technical advisory
committee to affirm the second
determination and to make the
appropriate findings.
>> all right.
Supervisor dorsey thank you
PRESIDENT Melbourne.
Colleagues, I am pleased to be
among those bringing this item
to you today together with
mayor laurie and supervisor
sartor.
Amendments were circulated
earlier I believe you have them
before you and I am happy to
support them.
I represent communities in the
east cut in mission bay that
are really blueprints for what
a vibrant mixed vice because.
>> can you hold on a second?
Could we lower signs I guess
are all right but the request
is that they be lowered so that
you're not blocking the view of
the people behind you.
>> there's a board rule that
indicates they should not be
blocking view and be
essentially in your lap.
>> so there we go.
Okay.
All right.
Take it away, supervisor.
>> thanks, PRESIDENT Mandolin.
Thank you.
Audience.
I represent communities like
the east cut in mission bay
that are really blueprints for
what a vibrant mix of uses can
mean to fulfill the promise of
21st century urbanism
underutilized and vacant office
buildings offer us an
incredible opportunity to
unlock more units of housing
and to welcome new neighbors
downtown.
In many ways this legislation
seeks to correct the errors of
20th century planning which was
overreliant on office only
downtowns and which isn't
serving our city well today.
Office to residential projects
not only contribute to our
housing goals, they also reduce
the supply of vacant offices
which helps to stabilize the
office market and by extension
our property and business tax
base that supports everything
our city does.
However, we are not currently
seeing these projects move
forward at the scale or the
pace we need.
This ordinance would help to
lower those costs by waiving
impact fees including
inclusionary housing
requirements for targeted and
narrow set of downtown office
to housing conversion projects
in the c-3 and c-2 zoning
districts and I believe it is a
reasonable tradeoff to make
when we are currently not
getting the impact fee revenue
or inclusionary units from all
these projects that aren't
getting built because of high
costs.
This ordinance is about
stimulating housing development
in downtown.
Both these conversion projects
and new housing projects
downtown and citywide.
And with that I want to thank
all the staff of the office of
office of economic and
workforce development for their
work on this the mayor's office
and of course our land use
chair supervisor melgar.
thanks also to supervisor chen
for your engagement and
questions throughout this
process.
I'm looking forward to passing
this today and I hope to have
your support.
>> supervisor chan thank you
PRESIDENT Randleman.
I also want to thank supervisor
chen for her work and trying to
figure this out in in and
really to look at this not just
for a short term growth but
really the long term impact
when you waive any type of
impact fees and in this case
the inclusionary impact fees
for any type of development and
project.
I would again put my hat on
when we think about the future
of our city, when we think
about budget.
Thinking about where do we
contain you'll be able to
identify funding to build
affordable housing.
>> those are real challenges
that we have to face.
And while I do understand that
you know, creating a waiver
which we have done about many
things for small business, we
typically didn't do these type
of for exemptions and waivers
with a sunset date because with
the understanding that you know
,once we do something a waiver
to be able to enact a fee or
enact a tax measure or increase
certain fees, it will be it
will be tremendously
challenging for the board to
take on.
>> and so principally I am
against fee waiver especially
those without some kind of a
sunset date or some kind of
condition and cap.
>> so I just want to thank the
mayor and thank supervisor
dorsey and thank supervisor
souder for coming really to the
table and to say yes, let's
figure out ways to boost long
term growth to boost the growth
of a space that really need
that growth for housing and
meeting that demands.
But thank you supervisor chen
for really thinking about then
what do we do to also make sure
that it doesn't create a long
term fiscal burden for the city
that we now end up losing money
for building more affordable
affordable housing and
inclusionary housing on site.
>> so with that I am today
in support of you've amended
and successfully we capping
this to a $7 million
7,000,000ft2 which I calculated
roughly probably about 7000
units of two bedrooms of
housing.
My assumption I don't know but
that's my assumption of that
and perhaps then that makes
sense for our area that not
only need the grove but the
city that actually needs it to
meet the demands of housing
elements.
>> so thank you supervisors for
working on this.
>> I do want to two centers if
I MAY thought through our
PRESIDENT And man domain to the
land use committee at this
moment that I do hope that this
conversation can be really
discussed in the committee as
PRESIDENT Mendo men have talked
about last last week you know
regarding another legislation I
think that some of these can
actually provide a longer
conversation and allow some of
these conversation to take
place.
>> it's not just because where
the committee is is is
delegated to do so but also the
stand will allow public
comment.
>> it will allow public
comments, allow the community
to have feedback about the
legislation and whether this is
something that we can learn
more about and perhaps there
are more things that can be
done.
So not just really an
afterthought of of adding to
today's and to the land use
committee and thank you so much
again to the land use committee
for your work but I truly hope
that we can actually have this
conversation took place in the
committee level allowing
community feedback instead of
full bore with that thank you.
>> thank you chair chan
supervisor sauder thank you
chair.
>> I first want to thank mayor
lori and supervisor dorsey for
their partnership on this
important piece of legislation
that will bring more housing
downtown and make use of our
city's excess vacant office
spaces.
Thank you to to chair melgar
for helping move this
legislation forward and land
use committee and of course to
supervisor chen for working
with us to craft today's
amendments in the committee we
added language to refer this
waiver to the inclusionary
technical advisory committee
tac as part of the feasibility
review that occurs every three
years.
in discussions with supervisor
chen we have agreed to go
further to add a clear boundary
on this program.
I'm glad we could come to this
compromise that responds to the
concerns raised by many
community organizations about
making this waiver indefinite.
So today I am introducing an
amendment to place a 7,000,000
square foot cap on the total
square footage subject to this
development fee waiver
in addition to two small
technical amendments that
accommodate the cap in the
legislation.
The reason being is by setting
a cap on square footage we
ensure that we do not
prematurely short circuit these
conversions at an arbitrary
date since we of course do not
know what the economy will look
like in the years ahead.
Instead the square footage cap
translates to about 7000
converted units.
That is roughly half of the
high end estimate made by
spurned agent gensler.
Of the number of converted
units that downtown could
currently accommodate.
So we're setting the stage for
this program to get us halfway
there and if and when it is
successful we can bring it back
to the board to revisit as
needed.
A copy of these amendments were
circulated before today's
meetings and have been passed
out as a hard copy for your
review with the amendments
highlighted in yellow.
This is a forward thinking
policy that will help us
revitalize downtown while
ensuring our city meets its
long term housing needs.
And I want to just pause to
remind us of the context that
we're doing this within a 35%
downtown office vacancy.
Many of those that we want to
return to office use but many
that we know in the 510 years
ahead will not have that office
demand and we need to think
creatively, creatively to make
sure that these can be homes
for residents.
We are behind other cities
in this effort far behind
in fact, new york city has 8310
units underway for office to
residential conversion at the
moment.
And it's not just our large
metros cincinnati 1753 units
cleveland 1690 and pittsburgh
1250.
San francisco does not make the
list of the top 20 cities that
have these conversions.
And with your support I think
we can get on that list.
Most importantly, we can work
to accelerate our downtown
recovery and accommodate new
homes for residents.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
>> supervisor sauder,
supervisor walton thank you and
thank you PRESIDENT Amendment
and I just want to start my
statements by saying I'm
completely all for these
conversions but I do think that
we are setting a trend here.
We've been fighting extremely
hard to be responsible about
development and at the same
time meet housing goals in this
city.
We have certain communities
that are suffering from
indigenous population flight
and on the brink of complete
extinction which goes even
beyond gentrification priority
equity neighborhoods such as
south of market and of course
bayview and district ten are to
be protected and growth must be
responsible and these
communities are critical to
true districts are in place for
a specific reason and that is
to protect these communities
from complete annihilation.
The rhetoric is that we need
housing all over san francisco
and that MAY be true but the
practice is we do not build all
over san francisco except
in neighborhoods with less
voice and most disenfranchize
us and in most cases that is to
be true and by the way we build
in district ten so this is not
someone who is against building
and against growth.
The original agreed upon sunset
date for inclusionary decreases
and fee waivers protects
affordable housing and aligns
with the goal to make san
francisco more affordable.
>> I know that there are people
who want san francisco to be
completely devoid of black
people and they don't want to
see a decrease in the wealth
gap but to blatantly disregard
community voice is ridiculous
and indicative of guaranteeing
that the democratic process is
almost nonexistent here in san
francisco we are on the brink
of setting some horrible trends
in this city and I hope that at
some point we start to listen
to community voice particularly
when it comes to growth and
building housing.
This coming from the supervisor
who actually builds housing.
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> thank you.
Supervisor walton our clerk has
reminded me that there is a
motion that has been made by
supervisor sauder and I should
ask if there's a second for
that seconded by melgar.
>> thank you.
Supervisor melgar supervisor
fielder thank you, PRESIDENT.
I first want to thank
supervisor chen and the 33
community organizations
including our culture districts
that appealed to mary leary and
my colleagues to amend the
legislation that was originally
introduced by the former mayor
that would exempt
nonresidential two residential
conversions from any
inclusionary housing
requirements affordable housing
fees and childcare fees.
>> the proposed legislation
will eliminate impact fees for
projects that convert office
space to housing in the soma
tenderloin, chinatown, north
beach and surrounding
neighborhoods during a time
when we absolutely need more
affordable housing the projects
that this legislation will
incentivize will be market rate
with no one side affordable
housing and will provide zero
funding for affordable housing
impact fees, zero funding for
child care impact fees that
goes towards child care
facilities.
>> the impetus for this
legislation doesn't emerge from
vacuum or even from the recent
past.
There is a long tragic history
upon which this legislation
builds and tries to solve for
between the 50s, late 40s and
the 70s the san francisco
redevelopment agency as we know
,demolished 14,000 housing
units in san francisco
including in these priority
equity geographies under the
auspices of slum removal.
>> this involved a complete
overhaul of soma.
>> it was in this time that our
S.F. Development redevelopment
agency director justin herman
said about soma this land is
too valuable to permit poor
people to park on it.
>> since then massive actions
followed the demolition of
thousands of housing units a
district court ruled in favor
of those poor and working class
tenants and a substantial
portion of the area has been
transformed into office and
convention space.
>> which brings us to our
present predicament of not just
an oversupply of office space
and a deep need for affordable
housing but also a budget
precariously tied to the ever
unpredictable booms and busts
of the exact downtown the city
created when it cleared human
beings and destroyed housing to
make way for big business.
And so with my vote I am
acknowledging that we need
housing in this area much more
than we need office space.
And I'm also warning that we
need affordable housing much
more than we need empty homes.
Thank you supervisor field or
supervisor chen thank you
PRESIDENT Colleagues over the
last few days I have worked
very hard to find common
grounds on this legislation.
>> I want to appreciate the
mayor's office for creating
space to meet with our
community leaders and also here
are their concerns throughout
this process the north star has
been now too we support our
downtown recovery.
>> why also ensuring a just
recovery for the working class
community in the downtown
in the downtown area.
I have urge our mayor's office
to ensure that cultural and
working class community share
that in this in the prosperity
and have a seat at the table.
The amendments proposed it
in this legislation by
supervisor salter establish a
limit to the number of
conversion of office buildings
to residential that are exempt
from community impact fee to
fund childcare, open space,
affordable housing, transit
schools and other community
infrastructures.
>> this legislation does as a
working class community to make
a sacrifice in the service of
our downtown recovery efforts.
I have worked with the mayor's
office to urge them to really
see our working class community
in this in our city wide
recovery and also our budget
investments and that we also
prioritize the needs of our
children seniors, working class
families and our most
vulnerable.
>> the 33 organization that
advocates throughout this
process have made a very strong
case that they have uplifted
the community needs and
solutions that pointed to the
need for added protection to
our priority equity geographies
and our cultural district.
For example the transgender
district, the soma filipinas
cultural district that lines
and within the scope of this
legislation these are
geographies that have borne the
burden of displacement not only
in the past but in the present
day.
I really hope that we would be
able to leave out this
community in the scope of this
legislation and when the market
kicks in and more office to
residential conversion occur,
we are ensuring that affordable
housing investment and impact
fees continue to flow to these
communities.
>> I am disappointed that we
couldn't go further to achieve
this carve out but however I
also want to say that is this
is only a month and three weeks
in file mayor's office and I
have heard repeatedly that and
we also have heard repeatedly
from our mayor that it is a new
day.
>> we are still finding ways to
work collaboratively with our
mayor's office and with each
other.
>> now it's the time for a more
comprehensive and proactive
planning that include community
and all impacted stakeholders.
The mayor's office has informed
me that they are willing to
continue to meet with our
community leaders to discuss
strategies to advance
affordable housing and
community stabilization goals
and I am putting a lot of trust
in the mayor's office and I'm
hoping that we can continue to
learn from this experience and
continue to build strong
partnership together if we are
taking away then we must find a
way to replenish the resources
that we're at for our working
class community that is needed
and deserve.
Thank you to all the
neighborhood leaders you all
have done a beautiful job of
educating our members of the
board and stepping forward to
represent the needs of our
community of your communities.
And again I want to thank the
mayor's office for hearing our
community and committed to work
towards solutions and thank
you.
And I also will vote today to
support supervisor salter's
amendment and the legislation.
>> thank you.
Thank you supervisor chan thank
you for all of your work on
this item.
All right.
So an amendment has been made
by supervisor sartor.
It has been seconded by
supervisor melgar and I believe
that we probably can take that
amendment without objection.
>> okay.
Is that a gavel of all thing,
MADAM Clerk yes, I'm gaveling.
>> all right.
And then MADAM Clerk can you
please call the roll on the
amended item on item 15 as
amended supervisor muhammad
mahmood I supervisor randleman
I middleman I supervisor melgar
I melgar I supervisor sartor I
sartor I supervisor sherril
sherril I supervisor walton no
walton no supervisor chin chin
I supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio and
engardio I and supervisor
fielder fielder no there are
nine eyes and two nose with
supervisors walter and fielder
voting no.
>> all right without objection
.
>> pardon me, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor one suggestion this
with objection this ordinance
is passed on first reading
MADAM Clerk let's go to our 230
special order yes, the 230
special order is the
recognition of commendations
for meritorious service to the
city and county of san
francisco.
>> oh.
Oh.
We're looking for cedric
spencer.
Can we okay.
Okay.
So could we get district heads
?
Great
.
You should bring the rest of
them in the chamber now we're
going to call it you know what
would okay, we we got district
ten in the room.
>> all right?
So for this final tuesday of
black history month, we will
begin with supervisor walton,
district ten.
Thank you so much, PRESIDENT
MADAM in colleagues today
during black history month and
the entire month we've been
honoring individuals whose
leadership and commitment to
equity uplift our communities
and pave the way for future
generations.
Today I am proud to recognize
cedric spencer, a distinguished
leader and advocate whose work
bridges the corporate,
legislative and community
spheres to drive meaningful
change.
And MR. Spencer, could you come
stand up at the podium please?
>> as vice PRESIDENT Of
relations at paramount, cedric
has dedicated his career to
advancing policies that shape
the entertainment industry and
beyond.
With 25 years of experience
working to improve legislative
outcomes for community and
corporate relations, his impact
is both broad and profound.
But beyond his professional
achievements, cedric's passion
lies in fostering equity,
ensuring that education and
innovation thrive in spaces
that have historically been
underserved.
Cedric's commitment to service
is reflected in his leadership
roles across numerous
organizations including his
board presidency at young
community developers leading
their growth through a major
pandemic.
His stewardship as treasurer of
the california state university
alumni council and his advocacy
as vice chair of the american
network for action.
His contributions to the naacp
california hawaii state
conference further underscore
his dedication to justice and
empowerment.
Cedric spencer is not only a
leader he is a bridge builder,
a visionary and an inspiration
to those who strive to create a
better future.
>> on a personal note, I would
like to add that I learned so
much from cedric about how to
become an elected official.
he not only mentored me
in fraternal roles and
positions but laid the
foundation and taught me what
was needed to successfully get
elected.
He helped me flesh out my
values, set an example and gave
me examples of how to be
strategic and keep the true
essence of yourself.
Importantly he taught me that
to be in a leadership role
requires you to set and live by
a certain example.
As we honor him today, I want
to make sure that he knows and
everyone knows how important it
is to have examples of
leadership that stay true to
their values.
On behalf of district ten here
in the chamber I extend my
deepest gratitude for his
unwavering dedication and
tireless efforts.
His work reminds us all of the
power of advocacy collaboration
and the courage to dream boldly
.
>> thank you, supervisor walton
and board members.
It is a privilege to represent
why cd the family here this
afternoon.
Today we are honored.
Today we are honored to have
our board members with this we
have MS. Tatum, MS. And MR.
Spencer.
Forgive my interruption.
Can you bring that microphone
closer so we can hear you
better?
>> so we have our board members
with us today MS. Tatum MS..
Andrew and MS..
Doyle as well as we have our
ceo and his executive staff MS.
Brianna blackwood jordan and
ms. Rock allowing.
Since 1973 the mission of white
cd has been to serve the
community of one point and
bayview and we still do that
today.
It is an honor to serve the
community and we will continue
to do so with that.
Again, thank you supervisor
walton and have a great day
.
>> next up from district four
supervisor and guardian, I had
the honor of meeting your
honoree this weekend.
>> thank you dorothy louthan
for any want to come on up to
the podium, dorothy?
>> I so this black history
month it's my honor to
recognize sunset resident
dorothy lathan.
>> dorothy is one of the first
black people allowed to buy a
home in the outer sunset.
Yes.
>> yes, it is true.
For many decades nonwhite
people were not allowed to be
homeowners throughout much of
san francisco's west side.
Baseball hero willie mays tried
to buy a house on the west side
in 1957 and was denied three
years later in 1960, dorothy
and her husband arthur were
able to buy their home on 48th
avenue.
>> she is still living in that
home with an ocean view at age
92.
>> dorothy has had quite the
trailblazing life from arkansas
to san francisco.
Today we honor her
contributions to our city and
community.
Dorothy made history with the
purchase of her outer sunset
home and she made history again
with her job.
She had to fight to become the
first black teacher at an inner
sunset elementary school until
dorothy came along.
Black teachers were only
assigned to majority black
schools and dorothy would
eventually become a school
principal and dorothy served
our city in many other ways.
>> she was appointed by mayor
dianne feinstein to serve.
Yes, she was appointed by mayor
feinstein to serve on the
commission on the status of
women.
She also joined mayor
feinstein's delegation to
abidjan when it was named a
sister city to san francisco.
And dorothy was a founding
member of the museum of the
african diaspora and she served
on its board of directors.
>> all right.
>> daughter was born
in arkansas and attended
lincoln university in missouri
where she met and married art
lathan.
Art joined the army which moved
the couple to san francisco and
art was sent to korea and
dorothy stayed in san
francisco.
Now when art returned they left
their rental in hunters point
and found the house they could
afford and the outer sunset
next to the ocean.
And they raised three kids
in that house.
Sadly, art passed away in 2022
after 69 years of marriage.
They had a joyous partnership.
They danced every day and they
traveled to every continent.
>> yes, including antarctica.
and today dorothy enjoys time
with her grandchildren and
great grandchildren.
She is loved by her neighbors.
Dorothy has many lessons to
teach us.
I love her zest for life and
her forward looking
perspective.
Despite having to endure many
challenges in the past.
Now here is one scene that sums
up dorothy at one of our recent
night markets in the sunset.
I saw dorothy with a cane
in one hand and a margarita
in the other hand and she was
bopping to the music, right?
Yes, she was.
So thank you, dorothy.
>> thank you, dorothy, for
being such an inspiration for
san francisco.
>> and now let's hear from you.
Well, all I can say is you're
going to kill an old woman with
all this joy.
>> this is so overwhelming for
me.
It's just unbelievable.
I have been on cloud nine ever
since I heard that this honor
was coming down the pad.
>> I just let me formally say
good afternoon.
Good afternoon to the board of
supervisors and to the
PRESIDENT.
But I've been just unable to
sleep.
>> unable to function.
I'm unable to write anything.
I'm glad this day has come and
I'm glad this day is going to
end.
>> it's just been too much
excitement for an old woman.
>> but what I'd like to do is
give a tribute to my husband.
>> my husband made me aware of
the value of feel at the
therapy and service.
And we have had so many
interesting functions that
we've performed in the city
that have brought us so many
rewards and so many friends.
>> and I'm just so happy to be
able to say that I have a room
full of friends back here with
me.
Thank you.
I'm happy to be there in my
family and just so thrilled to
have been a part of the
development and growth of this
wonderful city.
Thank you so very much.
She's right.
Oh, it's right outside the me.
>> it's good to see you.
Judge dearman.
>> oh my GOD.
Look at, uh, barbara from
district five supervisor mahmud
.
>> thank you, PRESIDENT.
I'd like to call mike carter
and the gas field services team
from virginia up front.
We should cfl board members and
audience.
We've all heard the news of
devastating wildfires that
broke out and threatened los
angeles last month becoming
some of the most destructive
in our state's history.
And our thoughts are with those
who are dealing still with that
an unimaginable loss in a
situation where many were
fleeing.
Amidst that crisis there were
51 brave workers from the gas
and fleet members of pge and
from the bay area who
volunteered to go towards the
fire to help our neighbors
in southern california.
>> and jan, these gas and
electric crews went to support
southern california edison.
Los angeles department of power
and water and southern
california gas customers who
were affected by the
unprecedented wildfires.
Pge also lent two of its
blackhawk helicopters to assist
cal fire in aerial firefighting
to help contain the flames.
Providing this mutual
assistance is a hallmark that
we should be celebrating.
And my partner and his team
want to would love to command
and accept have you accept this
on behalf of your colleagues?
There are over 30 folks here
today from this gas and fleet
team.
I'd like to commend their
bravery, hard work and
dedicated service to others
you've demonstrated in your
courageous mutual assistance
work.
Your actions have restored a
sense of normalcy for many
going through some of their
worst times.
And we are proud of your work
and hope you're proud to
represent the bay area and all
the good work that you do as
well.
>> so I'll say a few words.
Yeah.
>> oh first.
>> first I would like to say
thank you on behalf of pge for
the city of san francisco for
recognizing honoring the pge
employees that went down to
L.A. To support the restoration
effort.
Second, I would definitely like
to recognize people from the
bay area that came from san
francisco and peninsula area
specifically to go out there
and support for over a few
weeks to make sure that we were
able to provide the customers
in L.A. The support they needed
to get their gas and electric
restored.
So thank you so much for the
honor and we really appreciate
it.
And then as easy that we help
help on district six supervisor
matt dorsey.
>> thank you PRESIDENT Mandolin
you want to come on up?
So today I am honored to
recognize a man whose
dedication has left an
indelible mark on six district
six neighborhoods I represent
in san francisco citywide.
We today celebrate someone
whose leadership and service
have transformed our streets,
uplifted our neighborhoods and
restored community pride.
Ladies and gentlemen, christian
martin, executive director of
the soho community benefit
district and step up for with
with more than a decade of
experience managing community
benefit districts.
Christian has worked tirelessly
to make west soma streets and
sidewalks cleaner, safer and
more welcoming.
His leadership in launching the
summer west cbd in MARCH 2020
was a defining moment
establishing the operational
and financial structures needed
to support businesses,
residents and visitors.
We know the challenges facing
san francisco streets public
drug use, graffiti, illegal
dumping and myriad safety
concerns.
these are complex but christian
has never shied away from them.
He has met each challenge with
innovation, collaboration and
an unwavering commitment to
progress.
Under his leadership somewhere
cbd has become a driving force
in street cleaning, public
safety and community
engagement.
His work is evident
in thousands of pounds of trash
removed in countless graffiti
abatement tags.
In proactive and compassionate
outreach to unhoused
individuals.
But christian's impact goes far
beyond cleaning up the streets
.
He has improved city response
times integrated technology
into service delivery and
championed policies that
strengthen our urban
infrastructure and contribute
to a high quality public realm
.
His leadership was instrumental
in expanding the city's
connected worker app pilot,
allowing real time referrals
for cleaning and maintenance
requests, setting a new
standard for managing public
spaces.
Christians dedication extends
beyond soma west as the leader
of the ocean avenue
association, he is ensuring yet
another part of our city
benefits from his leadership.
His service on the board of the
episcopal community services of
san francisco too reflects his
deep commitment to addressing
the root causes of poverty and
homelessness.
This kind of selfless long term
dedication is rare.
It is the kind of leadership
that inspires action, builds
trust and fosters true
progress.
The kind of leadership our city
needs.
Christian's work is isn't
always easy nor is it always
glamorous.
But it is really necessary.
It is impactful.
It is transformative.
So christian, on behalf of my
own neighbors and district six
residents I represent business
owners advocates who have
benefited from your tireless
work and leadership.
Thank you.
Thank you for your leadership,
for your vision and for showing
us what it means to have a
community with heart integrity
and dedication.
>> please join me in giving a
warm welcome to two christian
martin and brody.
>> let's say a few words up and
then I think after this we've
got a couple of my colleagues
who also want to say some nice
words about you.
>> okay.
We'll brief resident
supervisors.
>> tall, handsome GOD, good
skin.
Got all his teeth.
Now that's a superhero.
I met anybody who can help out
the soma or san francisco is a
true superhero.
>> but when he asked us to jump
matt, guess what we're going to
jump.
With or without a parachute.
>> when he says bring the army
down we come in and we're going
to come for a fight.
>> those firemen because of a
brother who is a leader and who
has integrity, who is humble
but is down for the people.
And so christian,
congratulations, brother.
>> that's my brother from
another mother.
>> from the same father.
Yeah.
You hear me though?
GOD, that is a real player.
>> randy, I got to give it to
you the way I give it to you,
right?
I don't even know I was going
to speak today.
>> but I'm honored to share you
know, share what I feel about
you.
I think about you, christian.
You are real.
Thank you, man.
For what you do for the people
because it's not only for the
people you do it with the
people.
>> GOD bless you.
King.
And now we'll bring up chris
garcia.
>> thank you, rudy supervisor
chan.
Hi.
I want to echo I want to echo
that the west side is
incredibly lucky to share you
christian, with soma just to
say a little thing that was
very touching.
He is officially still on
maternity leave but he still
goes in person.
>> joy's meeting so I
appreciate you.
I appreciate your dedication to
serving the corridor business
corridor on ocean avenue.
>> thank you.
so I want to continue to remind
that your vision and your
tenacity have has so many
positive positive impacts on
the ocean avenue corridor.
We have the best version of the
corridor going back decades.
>> our streets are cleaner and
we have street activation and
large community events like the
last weekend's lunar new year
celebration in large enlarge.
>> I want to make sure that I
thank you and thank you and
your leadership at oira and I'm
looking forward to continue to
work closely together with you.
So then we can continue to
bring positive attention and
prosperity to ocean avenue and
thank you for all you do, chris
thank you.
Supervisor melgar thank you.
>> so people made me wondering
you know this is the so my
supervisor in how come you know
district 11 is district seven.
So in fact you know when I
became supervisor with her at
the ocean avenue association
was going through some
leadership difficulties.
>> we have an organization that
had been around for a while.
People were not believing
in the mission.
Things were a little bit tired
and with a collaboration and
long coordination with chris
gorga that you would then I
insisted that we help the to
lean into who they are and hire
a professional executive
director.
>> but you know being poor as
we are it was a tall order
because you know we couldn't
pay you know who we needed but
we found that unicorn.
And that is creation and who we
share with district six and
soma.
And you are one of a kind
because not only do you bring
all of the professional
experience expertise, you know
what you're doing but you are
also one of the gentlest,
kindest, most intelligent and
emotionally intelligent people
that I've seen do this kind of
work.
>> and that's what we needed.
We needed people to believe
again in what we are doing.
So I share my colleague
supervisor chen's great words
about you.
I am so grateful that you're
there that you wanted to take
this up and to make such a
large part of san francisco.
So my and the oh, am I better
for your work?
So thank you so much and thank
you supervisor dorsey for
recognizing christian's great
work.
Thank you.
Supervisor melgar chris caucus
thank you PRESIDENT Mandolin
good afternoon members of the
board chris corgi step you the
director of the community
economic development
development division at I would
say that five times fast.
I'm here today.
I'm just so thrilled and
honored to hear about christian
martin receiving this honor.
I cannot think of a better
person for this.
When I first met him we started
around the same time he was
over at the lower pork cbd
which I think at the time MAY
have been in district three
possibly district.
>> I don't know how district
lines work anymore but I got to
see his work up close and
personal and when we formed the
western soma cbd back in 2019
finding an executive director
for that was a tall order for
the community and they found
what I believe to be one of the
best in the country not only
the city but the country.
This is somebody who is a
strategic thinker thinks
outside of the box and you
heard it from other folks who
say it much more eloquently
than I.
His empathy knows no bounds
during the pandemic he opened
up the soma west cbd to help
other cbd with their pandemic
response.
You could call him at any time
of day and I mean we had some
really, really late night calls
.
Christian you are an amazing
individual and we in san
francisco are so lucky to have
you and thank you supervisor
dorsey's supervisor chen and
supervisor melgar for your kind
words about christian.
Without further ado, MR. Martin
thank you chris rudy supervisor
dorsey supervisor melgar,
supervisor chen all the
supervisors.
Wow.
What an incredible honor to
hear such kind words.
This is one of those jobs where
you could do 100 things in a
day and someone will come along
and point to the first thing
and say you didn't do.
But excuse my language but
you've heard words.
I just want to thank my my team
as some of west if you could
just stand up because this
honor is your honor this is
this is a team responsible.
This is a team responsible for
picking up over hundreds of
thousands of pounds of trash
needles, feces, you name it
from the public realm you make
it possible for kids to go to
school without having to deal
with that, for seniors to get
past the sidewalk.
>> and I'm so proud of you and
the work that we strive and the
work that we've been able to do
over the past five years.
I just want to thank you all.
Mom, I want to thank you for
instilling the work ethic and
values that you did in me and
we've been through a lot.
>> we've been through a lot.
>> we're going to get through
the rest and just the some
community district six urban
alchemy united players all all
of ambassadors and
practitioners out here doing
the dirty work and making this
city livable.
I just can't thank you all
enough and I work for you and
I'm honored to continue this
work with you at my side.
>> thank you.
>> thank you very much.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Thank you very much.
All right.
Well, thank you very much.
>> all right.
Up next I believe district
seven supervisor melgar, you
are sharing a combination with
some of your colleagues
proudly.
All right.
Thank you, PRESIDENT.
Gentlemen, colleagues, it is my
distinct honor today to join
supervisors chen and walton
in commending the incomparable
reverend roland gordon for as
we like to call him in the
neighborhood rev g.
>> of the ingleside
presbyterian church.
Reggie just celebrated his 80
first birthday on FEBRUARY 13th
declared we are going to be
voting later to honor
resolutions occurring that day
as reverend roland gordon day
in the city and county of san
francisco.
>> reggie was born
in greenwood, mississippi
before moving with his family
to gary, indiana, where he was
a captain and star player
in his high school basketball
team.
>> former supervisor jairo
sandoval from district 11 once
quipped that michael jordan
owes his place as the greatest
pro basketball player
in history only because reb g
decided to choose ministry
rather than basketball
professionally.
>> reggie completed his master
of divinity degree in 1983 and
was ordained as ingleside
presbyterian church's full time
pastor.
After that and he's been there
ever since seeing the church's
immense potential.
>> reggie organized the
ingleside church basketball
league inside the church's
gymnasium providing a positive
space for local youth to learn
and play his life's work has
always revolved around building
up and empowering young people
to achieve their greatest
potential and moreover to
develop young people to become
leaders and mentors.
And a few of them are right
here today and many of them are
not here because they are busy
at the church or running the
afterschool program.
Reggie positioned his church as
a nexus for the ocean.
>> richard ingleside community
facilitating local organizing,
providing meeting space for
community events inviting we
now artists to address the
community and rehabilitating
the dilapidated feel and loop
hole which is now known as city
college station into a
beautiful community space that
you've all been to at where
many community events are held.
He's also well known for the
massive mosaic he has created
on the walls of the church.
His gym and lobby called the
great cloud of witnesses which
is a celebration of black
leadership and black excellence
and is an official historic
landmark of the city and county
of san francisco.
Reggie has been widely
recognized for his outstanding
dedication to his church and
the community, including
receiving the 1995 commercial
and award for his community
service.
The 2003 distinguished alumni
award from the san francisco
theological seminary the 2004
alumni merit a word from his
alma mater baldwin wallace
college and the 2023 national
jackie kennedy onassis award
for outstanding public service
benefiting local communities.
This is quite a man.
Reggie has left an indelible
mark on the ingleside
neighborhood and the wider san
francisco community and
countless generations of young
people who are now leaders and
mentors to others.
It demonstrates his immense
creativity, his talent for
revitalizing a struggling
spiritual community, his
undeniable passion for
developing new opportunities
for youth in his humble
leadership as a champion of san
francisco's african-american
community.
I am forever grateful to reggie
for his compassion and his
reminder that every person on
this living earth can do
something small to contribute
to humanity.
I will remember always the
first two that I time that I
met you that you gave me the
little cards with saint francis
prayer and I keep him in my
office and I give them to
people.
>> thank you for everything you
do.
And with that I'm going to turn
it over to supervisors chan and
walton to say a few word.
>> thank you, supervisor
melgar.
And first of all I just want to
take you will take the time,
reverend g.
>> to wish you a happy 81st
birthday and let you know that
FEBRUARY is most definitely a
great month.
>> but thank you for dedicating
your life to uplifting the
community through faith,
through education and of course
through the arts.
>> you've been a force for
positive change from your early
days as a basketball star
in indiana and ohio to your
transformative leadership at
ingleside presbyterian church
right here in san francisco.
Whether founding the ingleside
community center mentoring
youth through basketball or
creating a breathtaking great
cloud of witness black history
collage reverend g your impact
is immeasurable and will
continue to inspire generations
to come.
You are a true living legend
and I am proud you are
receiving your flowers today
here at the board of
supervisors.
And the last thing I would just
say is there are very few more
mature people who can still
connect with young folks in our
community.
And I am forever grateful of
you for having that ability.
Thank you for your continued
commitment and dedication.
>> good afternoon reverend g.
>> today I also would like to
recognize and celebrate you on
your 81st birthday.
>> reverend g has been serving
the community for decades
through the ingleside
presbyterian church.
He has been a force for change
and an inspiration to countless
youth.
>> and it's really my honor to
set the it it's really my honor
to declare alongside supervisor
malka supervisor walton.
FEBRUARY 13th, 2025 as reverend
monarch raven rono gordon day
in san francisco.
>> congratulation.
>> and I would also like to
take a moment to highlight a
few of your project that I
admire and have gratitude for
reverend g has done so much to
build cross-racial solidarity
to nurture our black and asian
unity and also to advocate for
restorative justice for
communities of color.
In 2019 the first ever lunar
new year celebration on ocean
was hosted in your church.
>> why this event has now been
moved to the unity plaza with a
stage and booths.
But I want to continue to make
sure that we recognize the hard
work the work that you have put
in reverend g to did it that
you kicked off you take the
community to kick off this
event.
>> thank you.
And I also remember that you
welcomed me to have a lunar new
year presentation with the kids
in the afternoons in the
afterschool program last year.
>> and I also appreciate and I
really enjoyed it.
I enjoyed it and I really
enjoyed it.
The celebration with the
children's in the program.
And thank you again for
continue to bridging that
cultural and celebrating with
us and also found the ingleside
community center in 1986 and
afterschool program that foster
youth and community development
for predominantly black and
brown kids which I witnessed
that and today.
>> this is really a space for
black and asian kids to build
relationship friendship and
solidarity.
Thank you for that.
I also want to commend your
contribution to the food pantry
and assisting our most
vulnerable community members
especially during pandemic.
>> reverend g has left an
incredible mark on the
ingleside neighborhood as well
as the city in general.
>> he is an inspiration open
and fierce advocates especially
for the youth.
>> for all your hard work we
recognize and celebrate and
honor reverend g.
For your 80th first birthday.
Happy birthday and congratulate
and thank you and and I believe
the supervisor melgar has some
additional I just wanted to add
one more thing and that is that
in addition to the resolution
that we will be passing today
on your birthday and the
commendation to you, our mayor
daniel lurie was kind enough to
also provide our recognition
for you as well which I will be
handing over after your award.
So if you could come up reb g
and say a few words that would
be great.
>> but first I'd like to give
honor to GOD for my beautiful
mother and I have to mention
her MRS. Shirley lee wilson
gordon before I knew the hyde
pa I knew my mother and I know
that I receive in life I owe it
to my mother and then I met
jesus and it was understood why
the mother was so beautiful and
so I went on to her now praise
like GOD and I'm thankful for
that.
I love children and dedicated
my journey especially to young
american boys.
Many who don't think they're
anything think that our race
has done nothing.
I was inspired to put muhammad
ali on the wall when I arrived
at ingleside in 1978.
i don't know what city been
in crises at that time and the
late mayor died and fine shine
helped me out senior citizen it
wouldn't even go to the
bathrooms.
The building was so dilapidated
I was first refused help
in that area and then I think
it was MRS. Johnson he came out
and he said you got it right
back to the mayor and they they
came through for us and
improved the bathrooms.
So in 1906 and many don't know
the history of ingleside that
ingleside the people in the
neighborhood began to formulate
the ministry as a result of
earthquake of 1906 1907 they
were doing various bible study
groups and stuff for people
though they hated it help those
living in tents at the
racetrack and out in ingleside
and and 1917 formalized
everything when I saw that
history of service of people
service to GOD through service
humanity became our thing
because we inherited serving
people.
That's the bottom line and
especially the young boys I
noticed the boys on ali and put
another picture up.
I had no idea all that these
years later that I could fill
up a whole gym in most of the
church and they thought I was
crazy.
But just as I was called to
preach the gospel I was called
to do that wall been I'll be
gone into glory but that wall
would still have value and
inspire young people of all
races and all people to that
you get to give GOD his dues
and no matter who you are as a
human being we all are the
same.
We all have the same
opportunities.
We're not all of the same here
but you got to make your way.
>> it's the bottom line you
can't give up on anything when
you got GOD on your side.
>> I want to put this short
because I want to I want to say
this that we really feel moved
to say this that this city was
named after saint francis of
assisi and you heard nelda
miller talk about what she
looks at every day.
I want to take the time to
honor saint francis.
What I do is I have their
parents have children to rehab.
They some as they have a child
to read this first thing and
every morning lasting every
night because the children are
being program for violence just
by being born in this world and
saint francis asked GOD to make
him an instant of peace and I
was inspired to to take those
words and make it into an
affirmation which says I am an
instrument of peace where
there's hatred I shall promote
love.
Well there's injury.
Pardon?
Well there's doubt faith where
there's despair, hope where
there's darkness light and
where there is sadness joy oh I
shall not so much because seek
to be console as to console to
be understood as you understand
to be loved as to love for it
is in giving that I receive and
it is in pardoning that I have
pardoned and I've had parents
to tell me to teach their
children correct type of
thinking.
You see the children all they
get the games they play they're
killing and to learn how to
love each other is what the
what the good books talked
about and what my mother
trained us to do and and
hopefully it will make a
difference with people all over
the world reading in their own
language the same thing and I'm
going to get them a little book
together and eventually get to
move in on that project.
In the meantime, for the last
20 years I've been passing
these cards out and a lot of
young guys and our grandfathers
and I started it all along and
san francisco has been good to
me.
I love san francisco.
My wife loves to travel.
She go she gets on a ship and
go where I say goodbye.
Everything you see in the world
read in san francisco and mayor
brown has a room and they talk
about the collage that I was
able to accomplish at this
church mere brown has a room
when and he comes he enjoys the
room this is one of his
favorite spots tells other
people about it and I just want
to mention this also I'm sorry.
I'm sorry I'm taking so long
but there's a group called the
who bus that travels all over
this country and many guys a
country if they come here, they
go around their countries,
those with you who bus has the
one in front whoopin the back
they just pull up whoever they
pull up at and the kids just
flock to play basketball.
Basketball teaches life
teamwork and we all know the
importance of that.
All the athletes and okay I'll
shut up my wife say I talk too
much but GOD is good and I give
them all the glory.
>> here's the bottom line.
Thank you so much, supervisor.
Each of you I have this young
man who was one of our kids and
now the head of our community
center and he's taking the
lead.
We will be taking over when I
move on or whatever but this
guy who to try I'm sorry for
taking up so much time along
with so thank you for having me
.
I.
For you to district nine
supervisor fielder thank you
PRESIDENT Today I would like to
honor MISS Jean harrell also
known as MISS Jean.
Unfortunately she is unable to
attend today's board his
supervisor riser meeting due to
health reasons but we will be
making a trip out to her shop
in the portola to present this
commendation to her in person.
I understand we also have some
slides or photos but MISS Jean
is the owner of ruth's uniform
shop and we're commending her
for her service to the poor
community for many years this
commendation is all the more
specialized machine is planning
to retire at the end of this
month at the age of 80 six.
>> MS. Jean has been running
her uniform shop at 2469 san
bruno avenue for 44 years and
for decades has lovingly
provided children in the
community with school uniforms
including multiple generations
of families who live there.
Working at her shop is in her
words a dream come true to MISS
Jean.
Working with children and
providing them with school
uniforms is the joy of her
life.
MS. Jean and legacy businesses
like hers represent the
multifaceted fabric of san
francisco neighborhoods and
lend their charm and character
to our portola neighborhood the
garden district she calls the
port of la heaven on earth
where people and neighbors look
out for each other.
Local artist arthur coke has
honored MS..
Jean with a mural in the
portola and hundreds of people
in the district walk by it
every day to see MISS Jean
doing what she has done best
for so many years serving the
children who will become san
francisco's future.
MISS Jean truly exemplifies
what makes san francisco great.
What makes district nine great
are hard working multiracial,
multi-ethnic communities and it
is my privilege to honor her
for black history month because
it is so important that we
uplift black residents and
black owned businesses like
hers and pay tribute to their
legacy as part of san francisco
history.
>> thank you.
>> all right, rodney jackson,
come on up.
>> the trouble with being the
board presidents honoree is you
have to go last so colleagues,
today it is my great honor to
offer a special commendation to
rodney earl jackson jr the
artistic director and
co-founder of the san francisco
bay area theater company also
known as S.F. That come rodney
is a san francisco native and a
graduate of the roots of ruth
asawa school of the arts.
He's an alumnus of carnegie
mellon university, a broadway
actor and director, board
member of the american
conservatory theater and san
francisco arts education
project and a district eight
resident through his work at
S.F. Basco.
Rodney creates spaces and
opportunities for bipoc and
marginalized storytellers to
share their stories.
>> he's built a community that
mentors young artists and
builds pathways for
historically excluded
communities to thrive
in theater.
Rodney has used his platform to
ensure that black voices are
heard in all aspects of theater
from performance to leadership
.
He's shaping the future of the
arts in the bay area by
cultivating and showcasing
unique talent.
Today one of his productions
this year the day the sky
turned orange is a time capsule
of san francisco from the
middle of the pandemic a time
when the end of the world
seemed to be coming into view.
>> in dark times we turned to
the arts to calm our fears and
stave off despair.
When the going gets tough we
rely on artists and creators
like rodney to help get us
through.
>> we thank you rodney.
Your city loves you and the
floor is yours.
>> oh, their floor is not yours
.
Supervisor walton as a
reminder.
Thank you, PRESIDENT Amendment
and I did not know you were
being honored today.
Rodney but I just want everyone
in here to know that this is
truly a young living legend.
>> if you want to be proud of
something in san francisco
you'll be proud of rodney.
>> there is not another person
in san francisco in arguably
the world that is more talented
and more altruistic than this
young person.
So thank you so much supervisor
malcolm and PRESIDENT Malcolm
for acknowledging me.
Thank you.
>> wow.
Thank you all so much.
I feel like I'm standing on the
shoulders of all the company of
people I was honored with.
It's incredible.
I'm only 34 years old, born and
raised in this city.
But thank you all so much for
this honor.
I stand on the shoulders of
those who came before me the
activists, the storyteller
leaders, community builders,
artistic leaders who made space
for voices like mine my voice
of a young poor kid growing up
in the fillmore with big dreams
to sing, dance and act and
wound up somehow on broadway
running a theater company
in our city a city that has
always promoted originality and
challenge the status quo isn't
just about producing shows.
It's about creating space for
people to feel seen and to be
valued amplifying untold
stories and ensuring the next
generation of bipoc and born
and raised san francisco
artists know they have a home
through S.F. Baca we walk the
walk supporting hundreds of
local artists developing new
work that reflects our diverse
communities and bringing people
together to understand the
things that make us different
while finding commonality.
We need that so much in america
right now and in san francisco
.
>> this is how we revive and
reimagine our city.
This is how we keep san
francisco vibrant, great and
thriving.
I support any adminis straits
investors these values a vision
that believes in investing
in the arts in our people and
making S.F. A place where
everyone can flourish.
>> and I look forward to being
called upon by this body as a
voice for artists and for
nonprofit organizations because
art isn't just entertainment
y'all.
I mean it's entertaining but
it's what gives san francisco
its incredible soul.
And lastly we had said barco we
would not have been able to
grow nor make the huge impact
we have over the past four
years without the dream keepers
initiative.
Thank you for supporting dji
and I hope you continue to
support initiatives that invest
in people of color, people and
artists.
>> thank you all so much from
the bottom of my heart.
GOD bless you all.
>> I got flowers.
all right.
I know that's yours.
>> all right.
>> well, I think that completes
our 230 special order.
>> and now, MADAM Clerk, can
you take us to our 3 P.M.
Special order items?
>> 21 and 22.
Yes.
>> the special order at 3 P.M.
Scheduled pursuant to the
PRESIDENT's assignment of this
file to the full board of
supervisors for a public
hearing and appropriate
consideration by the entire
membership of the board of
supervisors.
Item 21 is to consider a motion
consenting or dissenting in the
mayor's removal of max carter
over stone from the police
commission item 22 when the
board reconvenes is a motion to
well it's the same motion, MR.
PRESIDENT to consent or dissent
in the mayor's removal of max
carter ober stone from the
police commission.
>> all right.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
So again, colleagues, section
4.109 of the charter provides
that the mayor with the consent
of the board of supervisors MAY
remove a member of the police
commission that the mayor has
appointed.
On FEBRUARY 4th, mayor lori
sent a letter to the clerk of
the board of supervisors
removing commissioner marks
carter over stone effective on
this board's approval of a
motion consenting to their
removal and a motion consenting
or dissenting from that action
is what is before us today
unless anyone has any
introductory comments or
remarks I intend to provide
commissioner carter ober stone
up to ten minutes to address us
then if we did so if there is a
desire on the body we can talk
or we can go straight to public
comment and then after public
comment additional opportunity
for deliberation and or voting
.
So with that colleagues I will
invite MR. Clerk commissioner
carter over stone to come on up
.
MADAM.
>> not at this time, MR.
PRESIDENT, before the speaker
begins I'll just indicate that
230 commendations are over.
>> that is the appropriate time
to have your applause at this
point if you do support
commissioner oprah stone and
you want to show that please do
so silently just as such.
>> thank you so much.
>> please continue.
Thank you.
PRESIDENT Mandel men,
supervisors board staff,
members of the public and thank
you again PRESIDENT Mandell man
as I struggle with this
microphone for allowing me time
to speak I appreciate that late
one evening when I was about
seven years old I was abruptly
woken up in the middle of the
night I woke to the rustle of
the covers being yanked off of
me and my mother's voice
snapping at me to get up.
She disappeared into the next
room and I heard the muffled
sounds of adults arguing at the
time she was renting a room
from a family in concord,
california.
I blinked an almost like magic
she had whisked my younger
sister and I into the back of a
car and we were off driving to
an unknown destination on
desolate streets on a cold
cloudless night after nearly an
hour we parked outside of what
I would now recognize as a
crack house.
My mother told us she would be
right back and disappeared
inside leaving my younger
sister and I in the car.
I don't know exactly when it
happened but at a certain point
the mix of disagree and
tension, panic fright and the
sheer discomfort of being
in the cold car and our thin
cotton pajamas bubbled over and
I remember seeing tears flood
my little sister's eyes and
pour down her face and I
remember thinking that I
couldn't cry because I had to
be strong for her after what
seemed like forever, my mother
finally emerged from the house
and drove us home as the sun
was coming up.
Experiences like these and
others like it have made me
realize how incredibly lucky
I've been because they
highlight how my life could
have ended up so differently.
If so many things hadn't broken
just my way including having a
father who raised my sister and
I all by himself with so much
love.
This instilled in me an
enormous drive to make
something of myself so as to
not let this luck go to waste.
And it also gave rise to a deep
sense of obligation to help
others who had been less lucky
than me.
So when the opportunity arose
to join the police commission
and serve my hometown the city
that I love I couldn't say no.
I threw myself into this job.
I approached it with a care
devotion and seriousness that
it requires from the start I
was also acutely aware that
police commissioners occupy a
special place in san
francisco's system of.
Over 20 years ago the people
amended the city's charter to
take power away from the mayor
and make police commissioners
independent from the political
branches.
In my three years on this
commission I've taken the
responsibility to be
independent very seriously.
I have cast every vote knowing
that my first and only
obligation is to the people of
san francisco not to any
politician or political cause.
>> that means that when S.F. Pd
engaged in unlawful, unethical
and unlawful conduct I asked
the hard questions that needed
to be asked.
The questions that the public
deserved answers to.
That's what I did when it came
to light that S.F. Pd was using
rape victim dna to investigate
the victims of sexual assault
rather than the suspects and
also secretly storing the dna
of innocent people for
indefinite periods.
That's what I did when S.F. Pd
purchased drones without
seeking board approval
in violation of state law.
That is what I did when S.F. Pd
gave away millions of taxpayer
dollars to be spent on luxury
vacations and gift boxes.
These efforts to hold S.F. Pd
accountable have not endeared
me to the leadership of our
police department.
A lot of politicians don't like
it either.
They told me that that's just
not how things are done in this
city.
>> but my job is not to become
popular with the agency I'm
supposed to be overseeing.
It is to serve the public and
protect and defend the rule of
law.
>> mayor lurie never bothered
to meet with me and he hasn't
bothered to justify why he is
removing me.
But he apparently has a
different vision of the police
commission than the one set out
in the charter.
He would prefer commissioners
who follow orders and do as
they're told.
>> he's not alone in this view
dismantling independent
oversight agencies in the name
of efficiency is certainly
in vogue these days.
I'm sure many in washington
would applaud daniel lurie's
course political desire for
more executive power.
But I know that san francisco
stands for something different
and I imagine many of you do
too when the people amended the
charter 20 years ago they
envisioned that mayors would
want to exert undue control
over the commission
in precisely the way that mayor
lurie is attempting to do now.
And one thing they did to
prevent that was to force
mayors to get approval from the
board before they could remove
any commissioner today this
board will have a chance to
live up to this legal
obligation to exercise its
independent judgment about
whether I deserve to finish my
term or not.
>> but how you vote today will
have much broader implications
in this one removal effort it
will reveal whether the board
is willing to defend the
public's right to honest and
independent oversight of the
police department or whether it
will succumb to the mayor's
relentless political pressure
and shirk this obligation a
failure to stand up to daniel
lurie's unprecedented power
grab will call into question
the independence of every
charter commission and I fear
inflexibility writing harm on
our institutions and our system
of.
I would like to address head on
a comment made by one
supervisor who said that my
failure to resign showed that I
was not classy in his words.
Let let me be clear there is
nothing classy about quitting
there is nothing classy about
abandoning my commitment to the
people of san francisco to
serve out my term with
integrity and independence and
there is nothing classy about
bending the knee to a mayor who
would rather have a rubber
stamp in my place.
>> yeah, I will continue to
fight for an independent police
commission free from undue
political influence and I hope
that you will too.
Finally, everything I've done
on this commission is for my
son everett with the hope that
one day he might grow up in a
better, safer and freer san
francisco.
>> there's been so many times
on this commission where I've
had to make a choice between
doing what is easy and doing
what is right.
I've made every choice with the
hope that one day when everett
is old enough to understand he
might be proud of me.
>> appearing before this board
today to advocate for the
public's right to independent
citizen oversight wasn't the
easiest choice I could have
made.
But it is the right thing to do
.
My hope is that you will all do
what you feel is right today.
>> yeah.
Thank you PRESIDENT Mandolin.
Thank you for seeing no names
on the roster.
>> we will go to public comment
.
I'm going to ask folks to line
up your folks to line up over
on your right our left of
westfield there on the fielder
was on the roster oops do you
undo that after okay I did not
I apologize okay well I
apparently feel there was on
the roster and I didn't see her
do we want to hear from
supervisors first or public
comment first supervisors first
public comment first come
public comment first any.
All right.
Well we got two folks dorsey
and chan.
Do you it's your call I don't
tell you do this with it all
okay.
>> all right.
Public comment.
Okay.
I'm going to be superficial.
please try to do this then
because we don't want to spend
all day here.
I just told max I used to call
him man max over there is just
steady soul.
He just did he saved his soul.
I hope you're going to do this
then because you are.
>> your soul is under arrest,
understand?
You just did it saved his soul.
No is good.
He has nothing to fear.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome, MR. CHAIRMAN.
Thank you, angela.
Real and the woman next to you
.
How do you spell I say alyssa
you okay?
>> I didn't I last time was
here two weeks ago.
>> I didn't recognize MR.
Ahmed.
Forgive me.
This is not general public
comment.
>> I am because I want to let
the full board thank you for
working on affordable housing
but I need to make a little
adjustment there.
Nimbys low income housing and
section eight affordable
housing is market rate housing
we have enough for that low
income and section eight.
I want to thank matt dorsey for
going to manny's cafe and
supervisory ralph amendment
addressing anti sentiments and
the ceo of jewish community
relations council anti
sentiments has been around I
don't know how long but many
throughout the centuries and I
hope it will be addressed well
it is addressed by know
schwarzenegger and I hope it
will get better everywhere
somehow you've come a long way
baby.
>> you supervisor alfred
benjamin yes.
There's another thing in my
neighborhood present shops and
in my neighborhood everything
was right.
>> you're a strong
neighborhood, MR. Allman.
>> excuse me.
There's no MR. Ormond this is
not general public comment.
This is very specific public
comment on the well, I'm going
to read all of you paid a
ticket a parking ticket out of
my own pocket.
So power to the people.
>> thank you, MR. CHAIRMAN.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker,
MR. Washington okay.
>> so listen, supervisors I
guess is going to be more your
first big decisions here again
.
So our current mayor he was
just in the fillmore and you
did a tour up and down fillmore
got a chance to meet him.
He seems like a pretty
reasonable guy.
He's the mayor.
He's a millionaire or he's
here.
>> but the way people was
talking back there comparing
him to a trump type of
administration now the police
department I was I'm known for
going to the police department
commissioners for years.
I never met this commissioner
but he seems like a people's
person and I'm not clear
understanding why the mayor
wants to remove this jim and it
must be some politics behind
the politics are full of
tricks.
Makes you turn to a lunatic but
I don't know what's going on.
But the mayor I wish you would
consider is you're removing
because you got so much support
for this gentleman here.
It seems like we team you up
against trump and I know you're
not a trump sister but you a
millionaire.
But I do believe you have
passion in your heart so I
would suggest that you
recommend and suggest that you
repass this and just turn it
back over to him and let the
man stay in his position.
I think he's doing a wonderful
job now I haven't been to the
police commissioners so far but
I do know when they set the
this new PRESIDENT For some of
the police department 20 years
ago, that's when I was going to
the police commissioners often
so I got to visit it.
But I'm here supporting the
young man.
He seems to be an upright
person to me so mayor, you
better check yourself before
you be by yourself.
>> thank you, MR. Washington.
All right.
Welcome, MISS Brown.
>> I like to u the overhead.
I'm here in support of max
carter always.
Don't you see this?
He has made a resolution for to
show that unsolved homicides
I'm a mother who've lost a
child to murder and I've been
at the police commission every
wednesday I've been there
longer and some of them that
have come come and go come and
go but none none of them have
never done what max carter has
done.
You see this resolution for two
paid tipsters to to come forth
for four homicides, cold cases
who has never no one has never
done this and I commend him and
I'm really sad that that
they're going to get rid of
them.
>> look at these unsolved
homicides.
>> tell me how many mothers are
going to are going to be happy
when our cases get solved.
>> look at them.
Look at these unsolved
homicides, all of them look at
them.
Look at what I have to deal
with MARCH quarter over stone
has given me some some hope
hope this is what they left me
of my son.
Look at all the unsolved
homicides so you can put the
camera back on me.
>> but I just want to say to
laurie please let him finish
his year.
Let him finish.
You just he just read you
something about his family and
his mother.
I'm pretty sure you have
children.
I've been around you and I seen
you seem to be a nice mayor.
Please give this young man a
chance.
He has done great things and
there's no misconduct from him.
>> so please give him another
chance.
>> as a mother I need people
like him.
I'm asking the board of
supervisors my district, my
supervisor but lab to help lead
.
>> thank you, MISS Berry for
their help.
>> you just saw the pictures.
>> thank you, paula.
Tell me tell me just a sad this
is really sad but we have to
say that every year we I'm a
big thank you for your comments
,laurie.
You thank you.
>> welcome gloria barry gloria
barry, district ten citizen.
First I want to thank you max.
Thank you for all your hard
work in I hope after today you
will be continue in the hard
work.
>> I apply for the police
commission twice.
>> I never was so happy that I
never got a position in my life
because now that I see after
the years of watching work MR.
I don't want to put your name
but just say max all the work
he's done in the work that
those folks had to do without
getting paid.
>> I didn't have the capacity
at that time to do all that
hard work and we ought to be
grateful.
>> I say I wasn't going to come
down here in a while after the
land use committee kicked the
black asian community in the
face on the safe way issue then
I'm watching this mayor and he
hasn't did a formal meeting
with the black fillmore
alliance.
He hasn't done a formal meeting
with the black employee.
I don't want to say their title
wrong but that's two three
times in a row where it's like
forget black and brown people.
But now I'm here because a vote
to remove someone at a hearing
and there's no reason why where
is the suits?
>> that's usually sit at a
hearing to present evidence of
why you should vote a certain
way.
Where is that information?
I've been waiting on it but I
do not see it.
>> so for anybody who needs the
cozy up to the mayor and vote
his way so you can get a deal
or walk in a video I'll take
talk with him or in your future
endeavors to climb the ladder
so you need that billionaire
money we see you.
>> we see you.
>> thank you.
Gloria berry, welcome to the
next speaker.
>> I really don't think that I
need that much announcement but
I'm retired captain yolanda
williams, the PRESIDENT For a
long time of the officers for
justice and you know that I was
a victim of tax gate.
>> the racist text messages
sent by police officers.
The motivation behind the un
warranted removal of
commissioner carter.
>> oprah stone is becoming
increasingly clear to me.
>> it appears that this action
is intended to consolidate the
support within the commission
to eventually remove chief
william scott and to facilitate
the appointment of chief of
public safety.
>> paul yep.
San francisco has had enough of
the backdoor dealings and the
pay to play politics.
>> are we striving for a new
era in our city?
Unfortunately this situation
reflects the same old patterns
discussions MAY behind closed
doors while the public is left
with the mere facade.
Consider the legacy you wish to
leave behind.
Do you want to be associated
with such trump like divisive
tactics?
Or do you want to be part of
the new S.F. Trump collector's
club you set?
This was going to be a new san
francisco mayor daniel laurie
even ray charles could see
through this if he was alive.
>> thank you for your attention
to this troubling passing
pressing issue during black
history month.
>> oh and by the way, there is
no other acceptable black
american to replace over stone.
And while you are doing all of
this during black history
month, I want you to know this
is my 69 years of living and I
am born also in FEBRUARY.
This is the most shameful black
history month in 2025 that I
have ever ever witnessed.
And san francisco.
You should be ashamed of
yourself.
Shame on you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to the next speaker.
Good afternoon.
My name is rosario cervantes
and I'm a concerned citizen
that lives in district 11.
>> I believe I'm going to thank
max carter ulverstone for his
work.
>> he's he is really
conscientious.
He has integrity.
He's a lawyer.
I mean he knows the practices.
He we need him here.
He's done nothing wrong.
And I'm looking at some of the
supervisors that want to remove
him.
>> and it's just a shame
because it is black history
month.
I want to say he's a leader.
Let's honor him.
It's black history month today
and why did we bypass the rules
committee and come to this
board of supervisors meeting?
It's really a shame.
I think it's all about
oversight.
>> it's about human rights.
It's also about civil rights.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Please vote against removing
him.
>> welcome to our next speaker
.
>> hello, I'm here to speak for
max carter over stone.
>> I think he has done an
incredible job.
He has stood up against the
forces of fascism that are
obviously eating the entire
country including and
especially this board of
supervisors.
>> we have decided that our
police don't need any limits.
We've decided that our police
should beat the daylights out
of anyone that's convenient for
our city to maybe prosper.
>> I don't believe that that's
a sane decision.
I want rights.
>> now this is clearly not the
intention of the vast portion
of our mechanized abusive
bureaucracy.
And we have someone standing up
for our rights.
And so what is that person
gotten for it?
Single out specifically and bro
under the boot of our fascism
under your fascism.
>> you want to stand here today
and say that one single voice
on the police commission is too
much.
We can't have one single voice
of oversight.
We can't have a voice of
stability standing up for our
people.
>> instead instead the boot
must grow larger.
The boot must grind harder.
The boot is ineffective.
The boot has never worked.
The reliable resolve of the
boot is more overdoses and more
violence in our community every
time we've tried it and we've
tried it for 60 years over and
over again we've tried the same
drug war and the result of the
same drug war has been an
escalation from opium to heroin
,from heroin to fentanyl and
from fentanyl design design
in our streets which is
thousands of times more potent
as fentanyl.
Now why is it on our streets?
Why are the homeless in our
communities flesh rotting from
their bones?
Because of your failure to do
your jobs, your failure to do
the oversight that is so
desperately called for over our
unprecedented and unaccountable
police state?
>> thank you for your comments
.
Thank you.
Welcome to our next speaker.
Please.
Hello.
My name is magic.
I've been an activist since I
was 14 years old and worked on
proposition 14 which was to
make black people be able to
buy homes like that person who
was awarded earlier.
>> I've been doing this
activism and I have considered
san francisco to be the
greatest city in the world and
meant to lead us has they have
over and over again in civil
rights in gay rights, in police
activism, in stopping police
brutality.
>> and you sit here and you
will allow a mayor who bought
his way into this position who
doesn't even have the courtesy
to speak to our police
commissioner who has given his
honest devotion.
>> I have been to hundreds of
police commission meetings.
I have been at the sit ins and
the marches and trying to stop
the murder of our people by the
police.
I've been through 272 rulings
that the department of justice
made against our police
department.
And the slow pace at which
they've gone through this.
Now we are dealing with a
fascist coup, a christian
nationalist coup.
>> and you haven't said
anything.
You're not leading the public.
Where is your voice?
Where where's sherman walton?
>> for black history month.
>> come on, walton.
Come out here.
You're black history month and
we need to see you now.
Can you please direct your
comments to the board as a
whole?
>> yes, but I really wonder
about that ruling because I
need to be able to talk
sometimes specifically to
people.
>> so I think that rule is
wrong.
>> you're welcome to set up an
appointment in his office to
speak directly to him or speak
whatever she wants to.
Thank you for your comments.
My comments for the public were
blurry.
>> thank you for your comments.
Time's expired.
Yes, ma'am.
Shame on this for this takeover
.
>> >> thank you for your
comments.
>> are you?
Let's hear from our next
speaker please.
>> welcome.
>> good afternoon.
My name is valerie.
I am a fifth generation san
franciscan born and raised
in the sunset MR. And garcia.
>> I think today's vote is
actually a very easy vote for
all of you because whether
you're going to vote pragmatic
or principled vote it should be
to keep commissioner max carter
ober stone.
>> he's an exemplary public
servant confirmed by this body
to serve out his term.
And I don't want you to be
worried about the political
pressure that you're feeling at
this very moment from the new
mayor laurie.
I'm sure he will have something
that you can support tomorrow
that will not have the same
life or death consequences.
I'm here because it's not just
independent police oversight is
not just a political issue and
I wish that you weren't also
distracted at the moment.
>> this is a personal issue
in 1998 when some of you were
maybe just san francisco
curious san francisco police
department shot and killed my
friend, classmate and teammate
since first grade.
Sheila de toy I don't know if
you know her name but I'll put
her up here so everyone can see
on the on the screen.
>> so in 1998 sheila was
friends with a young man a
young black man who police
wanted in suspicion for
suspicion of drugs of all
things.
>> and they staked out the
place where they were staying
surrounded their car when they
were trying to leave, were
wearing plain clothes, did not
identify themselves as police
officers and shot and killed
sheila for doing it for no
wrongdoing and then went on a
spokesperson from the san
francisco police department
went on to smear her and say
that she was trying to live the
hip hop lifestyle which was
clearly a racist remark.
Anyhow, long story short, they
covered up the misconduct as
they had of the police shooter.
Many times before the police
chief dragged his feet to file
administrative charges and it
was too late because there was
a one year limit of there's
never been justice for sheila.
>> you know, thank you for your
comments, commissioner.
Commissioners thank you.
And so I thank you for your
comments and not necessarily
this one.
>> thank you for your comments
and everyone so we can get
through all of these
individuals who each get two
minutes if you wouldn't mind
holding your applause if you
want to show your support, do
so as such.
>> welcome to our next speaker.
Hello my name is amy bunn and I
live in bernal heights district
nine.
I urge you to vote no on the
motion to remove max carter
ober stone from the police
commission.
The commission is meant to be
an independent body, not an
accessory to the mayor yet
commissioner carter ober stone
exposed unethical behavior on
the part of our previous mayor.
Is mayor lurie concerned about
anything?
>> I don't know.
>> commissioner carter ober
stone has demonstrated his
willingness to act independ
ently and with integrity rather
than protecting his own
interests via fealty to the
mayor.
Lurie's office has not given a
good reason for this removal.
They just say they want someone
who will collaborate to make
our city safer.
>> that's a dog whistle we can
all agree san francisco needs
to be safer.
Our whole country and our whole
world needs to be safer but
safer for whom and by what
means public safety does not
come by way of less oversight,
less transparency or less
accountability.
Public safety grows when
citizens trust their lawmakers
and when those entrusted to
enforce the laws do so fairly
and ethically despite
meaningful police reforms over
the past several years, we know
that there is still a massive
racial disparity in the use of
force.
Commissioner carter ober stone
acknowledges this reality and
rather than sweep it under the
rug he continues to champion
appropriate and necessary
police reform in a city that
does need greater safety for
all its citizens.
>> removing commissioner carter
ober stone before the end of
his term is a politically
motivated move against a man
who rather than being bought is
keeping his eyes on the prize
and I urge you to vote no.
>> you're here and I am a
member of indivisible S.F. And
served showing up for racial
justice.
Those of you who want to be
allies look it up and get on
board.
>> thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker please welcome
good afternoon supervisors.
My name is erica wang and I'm a
constituent of district 11 and
a member of the indivisible
self.
>> I come to you today deeply
disturbed by a national trend I
see being played out here
in our city recently mayor
lurie reaffirmed san
francisco's status as a
sanctuary city protecting
vulnerable residents from
systemic inequalities an unjust
law enforcement actions a move
seen as courageous in the face
of an autocratic.
Around the same time the mayor
began his police overhaul plan
by asking an award winning
independent commissioner to
resign before the end of his
term.
>> only two other commissioners
in S.F. History have left
before their terms of office
both mired in scandal.
>> this is not the case here
something doesn't add up.
The only reason the public has
been given for this move is
that the commissioner isn't
collaborative but isn't an
independent commission meant to
ensure checks and balances a
core function of democracy?
>> independence means making
decisions based on principles,
not political agendas.
So what are we supposed to
think it is mayor lurie saying
he doesn't want an independent
commission to ensure checks and
balances.
>> perhaps the call for this
vote today is a political favor
for sam altman, ceo of open eye
,co-chair of the transition
team and technology expert and
the police overhaul project who
has a reputation for silencing
whistleblowers supervisors.
>> your decision today will
echo far beyond this chamber.
Do we want to uphold a
democratic institution or do we
allow political maneuvering to
enrich the pockets of the tech
billionaire without oversight?
I urge you to vote no on this
motion.
>> protect the people of san
francisco.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome.
>> good afternoon,
commissioners.
My name is paul wormer.
>> I'm district two and I'm
really concerned at this effort
to remove the commissioner.
>> and largely it's a factor of
trust and building trust which
is sadly lacking in this city
and it is affecting everything
from funding for transit to how
we deal with homelessness to
how we provide health care for
the indigent, how we provide
mental health services we need
independent commissioners.
It's great that the mayor gets
to appoint someone who has a
political alignment with them
but then they need to be
independent or the commission
serves no purpose when there
are four appointees from the
mayor on most commissions a
commission that serves no
purpose is a betrayal of the
citizens.
>> the country is different
than a business.
>> the city is different than a
business a ceo has significant
authority to make decisions.
There is employment at will
in california.
>> it is up to the boss to
decide who goes.
This is not the way it works
in a city where one needs to
develop compromise political
solutions that solve problems
but that listen to the people
who are being impacted by
actions.
>> and I will say in my 37
years in san francisco we've
heard a lot about police act
inappropriate police activity.
I am two words two phases or
three phrases come to mind.
Fahey two great cool new tools.
>> some of you MAY remember
those some of you MAY not.
But the history of the police
department not subject to
independent oversight is not
good and I urge you strongly to
reject the mayor's request.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> let's hear from our next
speaker.
Please welcome.
Hello.
My name is sammy and it was
mine and I'm the relations
manager for secure justice and
I'm speaking today to strongly
oppose the removal of police
commissioner max carter over
his work on policies like
limiting pretextual stops
demonstrates his commitment to
evidence based policing and
racial justice.
The california doj MAY have
ended its oversight of S.F. Pd
but racial disparities
in policing still persist.
We need strong independent
commissioners who hold law
enforcement accountable not a
rubber stamp commission
controlled by the mayor.
>> san francisco voters already
have made their stance clear
they've rejected measure d
which would have given the
mayor unchecked power over
police oversight and they
passed measure c to strengthen
accountability and ignoring
this public mandate would be a
disservice to the people you
represent.
Commissioner carter aubuchon is
precisely the kind of leader
that we need in this critical
role and his removal would
weaken public trust and roll
back progress toward true
oversight.
>> and so I urge you to stand
with your constituents and vote
no on this unjust removal.
>> thank you so much.
thank you for your comments.
Welcome.
>> good afternoon.
My name is earl hale.
I'm the director of the
criminal justice team at aclu
of northern california.
The aclu and our 11,000 members
in san francisco urge you to
reject the mayors effort to
remove commissioner carter
overton from the police
commission.
Before you cast your vote on
this important matter, we urge
you to ask yourself why does
mayor lori want to take this
virtually unprecedented step to
remove this police commissioner
from the police commission?
And if this is really about the
mayor wanting his own
appointees on the police
commission, why isn't he asking
the rest of the mayoral
appointees to resign?
Or why he's and he asking you
to remove them from the police
commission?
It's worth noting that
commissioner lary, for example,
was reappointed in 2022 and has
a term that expires at the same
time as commissioner carter
roberston.
However, the key difference
between those two mayoral
appointed commissioners is that
while commissioner oberstar on
carried and championed the
effort to limit pretext stops
and through the san francisco
police commission commissioner
larry carried his appointing
mayor wishes and opposed that
policy.
Removing a black commissioner
during black history month who
is a policing subject matter
expert and has advanced
impactful policies to hold sfpd
accountable and prohibit them
from their current racist
traffic enforcement is a dire
indication of things to come.
Do not let the police
commission become a rubber
stamp commission that fails to
hold sfpd accountable and to
the point about collaboration.
>> commissioner almost on led
the most collaborative policy
in the history of the police
commission when he led the
effort to limit pretext stops.
And this was done because sfpd
was a department that was six
times more likely to stop black
people, ten times more likely
to stop to search black people
for consent searches and 21
times more likely than white
people to use force on black
residents and only make five.
Thank you for commissioner.
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> welcome to the next speaker.
>> thank you.
My name's good afternoon
PRESIDENT Randleman and members
of the board of supervisors.
>> I'm barbara attard.
I'm a second generation san
franciscan.
My granddaughters are fourth
generation.
>> I've worked in oversight
in san francisco since 1983
when we established the office
of citizen complaints.
>> I'm a past PRESIDENT Of
nikole the national association
for civilian oversight of law
enforcement.
>> having worked with the
police commission for many
years, I'm I know how important
it is to have commissioners who
are independent and are
concerned about the importance
of policies and setting
policies that are within
national guidelines.
>> max carter over seven has
shown his serious commitment to
ensuring our police department
policies are developed to keep
all san franciscans safe and by
limiting discretionary stops
and passing legislation and
opposing legislation that we
voted last year to allow more
police chases.
>> we all saw the impact of
that nip add new policy with
the super bowl accident that
caused many, many people to go
to san francisco general
general hospital.
>> I've been told that this
shortsighted and wrong minded
removal of max carter over
stone is about the selection of
a new police chief when it's
time to appoint a new chief.
San francisco must do a
nationwide search and choose
the strongest chief for for our
city.
>> I implore you to do the
right thing to stand up to
mayor lori's self-serving,
highly unusual political
gamesmanship pushing the board
of supervisors to back him.
>> stand up and vote no.
Keep max carter over sloan on
the police commission.
>> thank you.
Thank you, barbara starr for
your comments.
Now welcome to our next speaker
.
>> good afternoon.
My name is rick girling.
>> I'm a resident of bernal
heights, a teacher for 30 years
and I serve usd a member of
ucsf.
>> and I want to say that
living in bernal heights every
time I walk around the hill I
go past a memorial to alex
nieto who was killed by police.
>> and you know, this was a
young man who was a security
guard killed by police for
standing on a bench protecting
himself from a dog that was
attacking him.
>> this is crazy.
And I want people like max to
watch over the police so that
things like that don't continue
to get done and unfortunately
in my district, district nine
just right around the corner is
a lady was saying we just the
average a&e just got its
parklet run down in a police
chase for I think stealing was
what I heard.
And I just find this really
appalling.
>> I would expect the removal
of people who do oversight from
trump, from vance, from musk I
don't expect it from the mayor
of san francisco.
And this is really beyond my
belief.
>> and I, I we need to support
this young man for what he does
and stop you know, the kind of
harassment of oversight.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome.
Good afternoon.
I worked on some of your
campaigns.
Let me remind you.
>> my name is wendy porter.
I am a retired teacher from san
francisco after 40 years.
I'm an immigrant.
I'm a parent.
>> I'm a grandparent.
And I'm just outraged.
i'm totally outraged that we
even have to be here to do
this.
>> MRS. Stir remember her name?
>> melissa sardo.
In 1990 she was murdered by a
san francisco cop.
>> and what I went through was
just outrageous also.
>> my sister was put on trial.
I wish there had been a max
ober stone carter for her.
>> yeah.
If you do this it will set a
precedent.
>> he what else is lori going
to do if he wins this one?
>> then you're sending him a
message that it's he can do
whatever he wants because this
is really, really, really bad.
>> I just I can't believe that
any of you any of you
especially some of you that are
being recalled would even
consider would even consider
voting yes on this do the right
thing.
>> have some done us have some
go on this.
Do the right thing.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Any porter.
>> speaker welcome.
Good afternoon.
Hi everybody.
>> I as PRESIDENT Of the police
commission sorry marie ravioli.
I am an eighth generation san
franciscan married to an
immigrant so since we're all
sharing that information I
thought I'd let you know as
PRESIDENT Of the commission max
carter over stone went far
beyond the very laudable goal
of police reform and
accountability and overstepped
with a very clearly clear and
strong anti-police agenda that
has impacted public safety for
the last several years and has
restricted officers from
enforcing our laws.
>> hold on one second.
>> the mayor has the right to
have his picks.
Any mayor has the right to have
their picks.
>> mayor breed had the right to
have her picks.
He does not have to and no
mayor has to honor the previous
administration just because it
does not sit well with some
does not mean it is wrong.
It is completely procedural and
it is completely within the
bounds of the law.
At the end of the day the mayor
is empowered by the charter to
have four picks on the
commission.
If the current mayor believes
that this particular pick does
not reflect the goals of his
administration, it is well
within his rights to request to
to remove him and to request
approval from this body.
>> thank you.
>> let's hear from our next
speaker please.
>> thank you very much, kevin
benedict.
Thank you PRESIDENT Randleman
and supervisors.
I have the privilege to serve
alongside commissioner carter
ober stone on the police
commission and I'm here to ask
that he be allowed to complete
his term the while as vice
PRESIDENT Of police commission.
I've gotten to work closely and
it's nothing you haven't heard
that commissioner carter ober
stone has been a fearless and
tireless advocate of
independent police reform
values which I think all of us
share in san francisco.
We've worked closely together
on a number of issues we've not
agreed on every single issue
but he is someone that can be
worked with.
I think I want to address
something head on that's been
the subject of a lot of
discussion which is whether or
not commissioner
cartier-bresson is
collaborative and I can tell
each I remember the board
supervisors to look past the
talking points.
>> I can tell you that he is
collaborative and I have a
couple of specific examples.
One is you heard that the vice
PRESIDENT Spearheaded the
effort to limit pre-check stops
here in san francisco and
in that process undertook the
most open, most collaborative
general order writing process
in the department's modern
history.
It included town halls, closed
door office town halls,
multiple focus groups and a
truly comprehensive process
that was collaborative in every
stage and every step of the
way.
Another specific example I'd
like to share with the board is
with respect to what's called
the preemptive deployment of
tire deflation devices commonly
known as spike strips.
>> last year the department
issued an order believing that
their use of them might be
outside of existing procedures
and stop that use.
In response to that and
in response to hearing from
rank and file officers, the
vice PRESIDENT Moved swiftly to
implement an order to
accelerate the return of those
to allow them to be used on the
streets because data showed
those were effective tools.
And finally just recently with
a body worn camera policy, it
was the vice PRESIDENT That
pushed us to revert back to an
earlier draft.
And in the end the final
version of the body worn camera
policy passed unanimously.
In large part thanks to the
tremendous work of the vice
PRESIDENT, he is collaborative.
He is a supporter of an
independent police reform and
should be allowed to finish his
term.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome.
>> hello.
My name is jordan neal,
district four representing the
electoral board of the
democratic socialists of
america san francisco chapter.
The members of our chapter have
asked us to provide public
comment opposing the removal of
commissioner max carter over
stone.
We're thankful to supervisor
jackie fielder for committing
to oppose his removal and hope
that her fellow supervisors
will follow her leadership
considering the commissioner's
record, it's clear why the
members of dsa staff hold max
in such high regard.
He's been a tireless advocate
for reform and transparent
civilian oversight.
The commissioner refused an
illegal order from the former
mayor to sign an undated
resignation letter.
In 2023 he overturned the spd's
attempt to circumvent the
police commission's oversight
by issuing two secret orders
without the commission's
approval.
>> he fought for critical
reforms against racist policing
practices in the form of
pretextual traffic stops by
voting for general order 9.07.
>> in short, it's clear that
the commissioner had a history
of taking firm principled
stances against illegal orders,
against racial injustice and
against abuses of power that
would harm everyday san
franciscans.
>> the mayor has asked the
board of supervisors to force
the resignation of this
principled reformer.
>> why?
The mayor has no argument
in favor of this ask.
There is no cited malfeasance.
There's no cited misconduct.
>> san francisco's voters have
repeatedly voted in favor of
independent transparent
oversight of the city's police
department.
They did not vote for a police
commission that simply serves
the interest of the mayor's
office.
Removing a commissioner who has
demonstrated independence and
integrity undermines public
trust in both the police
commission and in the board of
supervisors.
>> today I urge you to take a
page from commissioner carter
over stone's playbook and take
a principled stance.
refuse mayor lurie's political
interference in the police
commission.
>> thank you for your time.
Thank you for your comments.
>> you welcome.
Perfect.
Hey there.
I'm demar abe randy in district
three resident and a
representative home middle
club.
Like many here, I'm here to
speak in support of allowing
MR. Carter over stone to finish
the last year of his term.
I will say I find it profoundly
ironic that we just spent the
last hour and a half two hours
recognizing and honoring black
and brown leaders and
visionaries who dedicated
themselves to uplifting their
communities only to hear a
resolute resolution aimed at
tearing down another
immediately after.
I find it shameful then when
MR. Carter over stone was
addressing you.
Many of you didn't even have
enough respect to look him
in the eyes though you're
deciding his fate.
I moved here from the south
in hopes of escaping
miscarriages of justice such as
what I'm seeing today and hopes
of finally being somewhere
where I can feel safe in my own
skin only to find myself
surrounded by pseudo
conservatives and neo liberals
hiding behind a thin veil of
liberalism spouting hateful
rhetoric akin to mcconnell of
my home state of kentucky.
I found san francisco is not an
anti-racist city and instead a
city with a sordid history of
displacing black and latino
communities repeatedly a
history of racially biased
policies that unfairly targeted
black latino and arab
communities and a city
in support of anti vagrancy
laws that are reminiscent of
the jim crow south.
>> I found that when an
experienced, competent
individual comes forward to say
we should end the policies that
everyone in this room has
mentioned he is persecuted as
being disagreeable.
Which only leads me to wonder
what it is that this new
administration's plans are when
it comes to policing especially
when its head was recently
quoted in fox news as being
inspired by a former republican
known for supporting policies
that terrorized black
communities for over a decade.
We're facing an antagonistic
federal administration
trampling civil rights.
We know overpolicing doesn't
work and we know we need a
multifaith city approach aimed
at solving the underlying
issues of substance abuse and
homelessness.
Max understands this and we
should lead by example and
retain him because he will
fight for what we need.
>> thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to the next speaker
.
>> hi everyone.
I'm on your world.
Zimmerman.
I'm here in my capacity on the
electoral board of the
democratic socialists of
america as of chapter and I'm
in district three resident and
i'm also here to speak on
behalf of my own experiences.
>> why is the mayor removing
max carter oppression?
>> why is a critical question
and it remains deliberately and
disrespectfully unanswered.
Why would an independent police
commissioner be a roadblock to
mayor lurie's plans?
It's extremely concerning.
I expect you to dwell on this
and scrutinize what comes next
from the police commission.
>> if this isn't your fight on
public safety, we ask you what
is what is your fight on public
safety?
>> I had a whole tactful
statement but bear with me as
I'm inspired by everybody who
has shared to share what public
safety is to me.
>> I cannot express how many
times I've hovered over a phone
dialed 2911 and never called.
I never would ever think to
call because of policies like
the S.F. Pd's policy of keeping
the dna of rape victims.
>> that is violence.
That is violence perpetrated by
the S.F. Pd.
>> we can't just sit here and
talk about the police
department as if they are not
committing deliberate violence.
>> when you talk about public
safety, I expect you to know
that public safety is not the
cops.
>> I pray that none of you ever
experience what it's like to be
afraid of the police and what
they are going to do to you.
>> but I encourage you to
listen to those who are to know
that violence is in our homes
and domestic violence in sexual
violence and these answers are
not met by the cops.
They are so often not met by
the cops.
I ask you what public safety
really is and I tell you that
public safety is not the cops
public safety as max carter
oliver stone who has fought for
public safety from the S.F. Pd
.
>> he has stopped the violence
coming from within our own
halls of justice.
There is nothing more safe than
police oversight.
It is not a blank check to the
police.
You will see me here again and
again as we demand over and
over again.
>> and we thank you supervisor
melgar and supervisor fielder,
thank you for your courageous
justice on this.
>> thank you for your comments
,mike.
>> welcome to our next speaker.
>> hi my name is gloria
massachusetts.
I'm coming here as a d9 mother
and a public educator for many
years with S.F. Unified for
those supervisors that MAY not
have lived in this city back
when my child my children were
younger.
I learned about the killing of
alex nieto by the police
officers with 49 empty shell
cases up at the top of bernal
hill at the carnival because
someone put a table up there to
inform the public.
The police went to his home and
did not tell his parents that
they had murdered their their
child and ransacked through
their house and his car.
Amilcar perez lopez was killed
a block around right around the
corner from our home.
In that same time frame.
Louis pat gongora was shot
while sitting on the ground a
block from my house as I
brought my four year old home
that day.
>> I went to walk my dog to see
what had happened and police
officers all they had top brass
were there and that family was
settled with.
This is a matter of life and
death oversight does keep the
community safe.
I can't even add to what these
amazing speakers have said to
you today.
But I'd really like you to be
off your phones and maybe
listening a little bit because
there's been murders in this
city by the police and we don't
need to we don't need to repeat
this.
>> it is a matter of life and
death.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> it's just unbelievable.
Tanisha carlos of fillmore
district resident I'm here
today to express my disgust
with the mayor's attempt to
remove police commissioner
ultrasound.
What exactly does the mayor
mean when he seeks someone who
works collaboratively?
Because from where I stand,
commissioner oliver stone has
collaborated extensively with
community stakeholders
department leadership and
fellow fellow commissioners.
He simply hasn't shied away
from difficult questions.
I question whether the mayor's
definition of collaboration
might actually mean compliance
with a predetermined agenda.
>> is a stab is challenging
established practices and
advocating for historically
marginal marginalized
communities.
Consider it uncooperative.
How does removing commissioner
oliver stone advance public
safety in black and brown
communities?
What specific examples can be
provided where commissioner
oliver stone has been
uncooperative in a way that
hindered rather than enhance
public safety?
>> I strongly urge you to base
the decision making process on
facts versus personal opinions
publicly stating that
commissioner obra stone is not
classy for his decision to not
resign but rather fight for
those who need him.
Says more about the lack of
class in the person making the
statement than it does about
the person.
The failed insult was half bad.
If you want to understand any
problem in america you need to
focus on who profits from the
problem not who suffers from
the problem.
What is the profit to harming
and killing black bodies to
this body of of constituents
and to the mayor?
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome.
>> my name is christopher mica
.
I'm coming to this discussion
today.
I think about my friend in new
york who I found has been
recently made homeless since
the beginning of the year and
were was beat brutally by the
police in new york city a few
weeks ago to within an inch of
their life.
And I just found this out last
night and I talked to them.
I don't think I'll be as
articulate as folks who have
spoken already.
I think it's really great
commentary and but I'm struck
by the richness of all their
comments.
The citizens in san francisco
see clearly the politicking
behind this attempt to remove a
police commissioner.
We simply need independent
accountability and oversight
for the police removal of max
carter over stone who has no
ethical violations and has done
nothing wrong and pressuring
him to resign shows incredible
hubris.
>> and why why if this removal
is truly about making san
francisco safer, why is the
mayor targeting a commissioner
who has worked to prevent
police discrimination and
misconduct?
We need oversight that protects
all residents not just those
with political power or those
who can organize millions
in campaign donations.
I strongly urge the board to
vote no on this removal of mask
cover over stone.
And I want to thank jackie
fielder and myrna for their
support on this.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> oh no.
Welcome to the next speaker.
Good afternoon.
I'm janelle caywood.
I'm a 30 year resident of
district district three.
>> I'm an attorney for almost
as long and I'm here in my
personal capacity.
I've had the pleasure of
working with max carter over
stone for a number of years.
He is brilliant, truthful,
courageous and deeply kind.
>> max's only so-called sin is
that he doesn't politic nor
should he.
>> he's a family man and a
volunteer.
He has no political
aspirations.
He doesn't glad handle schmooze
kiss rings or brown nose.
He is collaborative
collaborative with people from
all walks of life.
>> when he's approached with
good intent but if you come at
him with cover ups bad data or
gaslighting, max doesn't play
as a commissioner.
He has taken bold and swift
action to protect the public
and to ensure that our policing
strategies are effective
evidence based and don't
impermissibly target people of
color.
>> max's bold action and
truthful criticism hasn't
always made him popular with
police brass.
But in the words of dwayne wade
big time players make big time
plays.
>> we as a community owe max a
debt of gratitude for
volunteering his time.
His rock solid ethical core and
his intention to do right even
when attacked in unfairly
demonized.
>> I am aware that max has met
with police officers off duty
in his own time who are
suffering in this trump era.
Women and officers of color who
don't feel supported by their
superiors.
He's compassionate and my phone
is full of these compliments.
Max's existence has made us all
who know him more ethical and
more courageous.
He is to be commended for
prioritizing truth, justice and
true safety over politics.
Working with him has been an
honor of a lifetime.
Whatever happens today, max,
thank you for who you are and
for being in the arena daring
greatly.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome nick.
Speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisors
on musc with care at the
council on american-islamic
relations and I stand before
you today in step with our
allies in opposing the unjust
removal of police commissioner
max carter over stone.
>> commissioner carter over
stone has been a persistent
reliable advocate for police
accountability and data driven
independent oversight.
Under his leadership he limited
abuse of pretexts, traffic
stops, expose corruption and
fought police brutality.
His removal would mean the city
of san francisco sanctioning
further police misconduct and
abuse abuse that includes
racist text messages, unlawful
use of force and misconduct
disproportionately harming
black and brown individuals.
>> the people of san francisco
have consistently voted
in favor of independent
oversight and against the
consolidation of power.
The city does not need a police
commission stacked with rubber
stamp appointees that erase
police oversight.
It needs commissioners like
commissioner carter over stone
to who rely on hard data,
listen to the community and
push for substantial reform.
His removal would weaken the
already diminished public trust
and erode the oversight that
the san francisco community has
repeatedly demanded and voted
for.
>> the board must push for real
cultural change within the san
francisco police department and
city hall not dismantling
oversight and transparency at
the expense of public safety.
So once again we strongly urge
you to vote against the removal
of commissioner carter over
stone and to let him finish his
term and deliver justice.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Your next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
PRESIDENT Benjamin supervisors.
My name is lawrence lee.
I'm a san francisco native and
a former member of a civil
grand jury.
And today I'm speaking as one
of the board members of the
advancement of victims and the
association for the advancement
of asians.
>> we are a new group that does
report cards on mayors and
supervisors and super
candidates on their votes.
And one of the key topics of
our group is public safety.
So this was a tough one for our
board to consider.
We really appreciate all the
efforts that commissioner
cordova stone has been doing.
We support his efforts at
independence accountability,
reform and oversight.
And in the end we agree with
mayor lori that we need a
commissioner that is for
collaboration and communication
for asian-americans in san
francisco from the richmond
district to visitation valley.
Have clearly stated over and
over again they want to be safe
for the grandparents and for
the sons and daughters of san
francisco not just
asian-american.
We would love to have a city
that's better, that's safer and
that's freer.
And so we encourage you
supervise others to support
this motion.
>> thank you.
Can we hear from our next
speaker please?
>> hey there.
Good afternoon, supervisors.
I'm caleb karam, a district
eight resident here in support
of max carter over stone.
>> as important as his many
accomplishments are, I've got
limited time.
You heard them from him when he
came up here and from the
community.
And the thing is I hope you are
paying attention because our
is designed to put y'all.
This board is supervisors.
The people have been trusted
for terms by the people of
their distinct neighborhoods
in charge of final say over the
removal of someone from the
police commission.
Your constituents are here.
I know they've written in.
>> please listen to them.
And I've heard there's a rumor
of this excuse.
The reason it's it's an excuse
it's not a particularly good
one.
It's not one that laurie saw
fit to tell the press to make
formal accusations about to
bring up before a couple of
weeks ago.
Neither mayor breed and I'd
frankly like saying he's on
collaborative or difficult is
heresy to all folks who have
worked with him or talked to
him or attended his commission
.
I would encourage you to let
max carter over stone serve the
rest of his term.
Florrie would like to have more
influence over the commission.
He is welcome to appoint
someone when max his term is
over.
>> thank you very much.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speakers.
Hi my name is lawrence berlin.
I'm a long time mission
resident, a labor organizer
in the tech industry and a
member of the harvey milk lgbtq
club board.
I'm here to speak today
in favor of max carter over
stone and more specifically to
lay out an alternative path for
the board of supervisors from a
political perspective.
I believe people have already
spoken at length about MR. Over
stone's carter over stone's
many positive traits and why he
should remain on this board.
>> people have spoken about the
legal authority of the mayor to
remove people and to make this
request that's absolutely
legal.
There's a reason that this
board has to vote for or
against that request and I urge
this board to delay that vote
that it can discuss a larger
move towards an independent
police commission whose
majority members are not
appointed by the mayor.
It is within this board's power
to remake the nature of these
commissions fundamentally so
that san francisco so that san
francisco can have the
independent police commission
that it deserves.
I urge you to keep max carter
over stone on the police
commission until such time as
you can make that change
because I assume it will take
time to work that out.
And his presence is the only
thing ensuring that the
commission has any independence
at this time.
>> you can delay your vote.
You can discuss this.
You can consider the political
ramifications of that.
I know that there is a lot of
quotes in the media from many
members of this board about
political capital, about
classiness, about
collaboration.
>> I believe that those are
things that you can work on.
>> I don't think that this is
the place to waste your
political capital with the
people.
And I would take note of an
article from mission local
analyzing the election results
last fall that indicated that
the most leftist groups in this
city including the one that I'm
a board member of had the most
success in their endorsement
in votes in both propositions
and candidates.
>> and consider how people will
be voting on all of your future
political careers should your
decisions not align with the
people on independence of the
police commission.
>> thank you for your time.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker.
Thank you.
Good afternoon.
My name you are welcome to pull
the microphone close.
There you go.
>> my name is alexi folger.
I'm a 31 year resident of
district eight.
>> good afternoon, PRESIDENT
Mendelsohn.
I'm here as a supporter of the
aclu and an appreciation for
the work they do to promote
genuine community safety and
police accountability.
I'm not sure I have anything
terribly new to say but I think
there's an argument for
quantity as well as quantity
just to reinforce the point.
What san francisco needs right
now is not to emulate what's
going on in the federal.
>> what we do need is
independent principled
oversight of the police
department and protection of
our civil rights, the
independence of the police
commission is more important
than the mayor's desire to
politicize it.
>> just today he got to fill an
empty seat.
>> did you know?
So that's his right in the
charter and that's enough.
The independence of the police
commission is paramount.
The recent police chase fiasco
is a clear indication that the
S.F. Pd needs clear and
continual careful oversight by
commissioners beholden as he
himself said only to the people
of san francisco and not to the
new administra ation.
>> removing a member of the
police commission or any other
independent commission for no
cause when they still have
significant time left on their
term will send a very bad doge
worthy message.
>> okay.
If san francisco goes the way
of doge where else can we go?
>> there will be no safe place
in the united states.
>> so as a white anti-racist
san franciscan my job is
solidarity.
>> I'm showing that today by
taking the afternoon off of
work to be with you.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker welcome.
>> please.
>> good afternoon.
My name's richard ivanhoe.
I belong to a number of
organizations but these
comments are as an individual.
First off, statistics show that
san francisco crime is down.
Its safe was safer in 2024 than
2023.
But more importantly I'm here
to talk about timing.
Others have pointed out that
this is black history month.
This is the wrong time to
remove an african-american
commissioner but even more so
we are sending a message.
If we remove commissioner
carter over stone that we are
aligned with what's going on
in the federal.
Not a message we want to send
to the rest of the nation that
service is subject to the whims
and pleasure of the chief
executive officer and the
billionaire donors behind them
.
>> so supervisors, if you can't
find the courage to vote no,
I'm asking you to at least find
the courage to postpone this
vote until things are a little
bit different in the nation.
>> thank you.
Thank you, MR. Avenue.
>> next speaker, please.
>> good afternoon.
I'm tab buckner.
I'm on the board of the
haight-ashbury neighborhood
council.
I'm going to speak briefly on
behalf of the board
in recognition of the passage
of bro both prop c and the
rejection of prop d last
NOVEMBER.
>> clearly your constituents
want to see less mayoral
overreach and more
accountability and independence
on our commissions which is how
our city charter is designed.
>> clearly we recognize also
the incredible work that MR.
Carter opus stone has done his
diligence, his dedication, his
not worrying about who's who
appointed him but what was the
right thing.
Working very successfully in a
collaborative manner with
individuals and different
departments in the city.
It makes absolutely no sense to
remove him at this time.
The mayor did not give him any
courtesy at all to meet with
him or explain in detail why
this is going on.
So first of all, I want to say
thank you, commissioner, for
all of your incredible work and
just on a final note, I feel
this is an embarrassment we're
having this going on right now.
An incredible waste of time
considering all that's on the
plate of this city.
And as others have mentioned,
we I'll bet every single one of
us is horrified as we listen to
the radio every day about
what's going on in washington
about executive overreach,
about complete disintegration
of checks and balances before
our very eyes.
If you really feel differently,
show that san francisco can do
it differently.
And just on a final note, this
vote that you're going to cast
is going to be with you for the
rest of your lives.
>> it's going to be a prominent
vote and it's going to follow
you everywhere.
>> so don't think you're going
to close the door on it today
because it's not going to
happen.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Tam buckner.
>> next speaker please vote
in afternoon.
>> my name is ping huang and I
moved to san francisco in 1979.
I lived in the sunset district
and currently live in district
one in outer richmond.
I speak against you guys
authorizing the removal of the
commissioner.
Many things have been said
about the commissioner and I'm
very impressed with what he has
done.
I wonder if if his real is his
real issue or the issue that
the mayor has with him is that
he is he's a known dissenter
and I say dissent is good the
right kind of dissent on behalf
of the right kinds of you know,
civil rights.
Those are those are important
dissents.
We have had many people in our
history who have who go down
in history because of dissent.
>> so if he is a dissenter,
more power to him.
I also want to note that I have
worked in the software industry
for many years and actually
in my most recent ten years or
so I've worked on collaboration
,software and collaboration is
his warm fuzzy word.
>> and I'm very disappointed
when it gets used in politics
like this.
People don't really know what
they want to say so they say oh
collaboration we want more
collaboration.
More collaboration is good.
I say dissent is the right
thing from people especially
people on an independent
commission who is supposed to
hold oversight over a powerful
source force like the police.
>> I also want to point out
that if you were in world war
two france to be a collaborator
is not exactly a compliment.
So I ask what kind of
collaboration is mayor lori
looking for?
What kind of collaboration is
he looking for from you guys as
a board of supervisors?
What kind of collaborator do
you want to be?
>> thank you.
thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker welcome.
>> hi, my name is norman
dahlmann and I'm a long time
resident of san francisco.
I support max carter opus stone
and I believe he is a very
important independent voice on
the commission.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome.
Hello.
>> my name is sherril thornton
and I'm the co-chair of the
harriet tubman african-american
democratic club, the only black
democratic club here in san
francisco.
That's charter.
I strongly oppose the removal
of police commissioner max
aubusson a move that threatens
the independence and
accountability of police
commission.
Commissioner carter aubusson
has led critical reforms
including any pretext stops
that disproportionately target
black and brown communities.
He's worked on.
He's worked to hold san
francisco speedy accountable
way advancing policies that
improve public safety.
His removal is not about better
governance.
It's about silencing
independents in oversight.
>> quote supervisor matt dorsey
recently stated that the police
commission served at the
pleasure of the mayor.
>> but that is not how
independent oversight should
work.
This police commission exists
to hold law enforcement
accountable to the people not
to act as an extension of the
mayor's political agenda.
If commissioners are removed
for doing their jobs for too
well, police accountability
becomes nothing more than a
political tool.
>> and let's be clear this is
trump style politics.
Silencing reform can
consolidating power and
weakening oversight.
It's shameful that this is
happening during black history
month at a time when we should
be honoring the fight for
justice and not rolling it back
.
I also want to uplift
supervisors jackie fielder and
myrna melgar for standing
strong on this issue.
Their leadership reflects the
values that san francisco must
protect.
This is not about mayor lori.
It's about the people.
San francisco must remain
committed to justice, fairness
and real public safety.
Vote no.
I'm matt carter.
I was still in the removal.
>> thank you.
And power to the people.
Sherril thornton.
>> next week is your history.
You're doomed to repeat it.
Hello, supervisors.
Some of you I have met with
in my advocacy work.
Hello.
Matt dorsey.
Hello, shimon waltz in and
hello MISS Connie shine the
rest of you I would love to me
some of you MAY or MAY not know
my story.
My name is christiana porter, a
very recent victim of excessive
force and police brutality
in san francisco.
As I stand here today, my right
arm is going down and tingling
with pain in the back of my
head due to that incident on
JULY 29th.
However, it's very important
for me to be here as I am a
resilient black mother of five
who needs her voice to be
heard.
>> it is very disrespectful and
a slap to my face that san
francisco not only is trying to
remove MR. Max carter from
creating the police seat that
caused me to get brutalized
which is that pretextual their
pretextual stop A.K.A. Stop and
frisk need I remind the room at
the central park five sandra
bland victims are pretextual
stops that should never have
happened.
>> with that being said, MR.
Max carter is being asked to
resign simply for having an
opposition oppositional
personality.
Isn't it a beautiful thing to
agree to disagree and come to
terms in middle ground?
That is the beauty of freedom
of speech.
That is why we are all able to
be here today and say our piece
right?
>> so in particular I won't
take up too much time.
However, I will say and end on
this note.
My people please understand
this and please be discerned
and watch body language.
They do not care about us.
It is time for us to care about
us.
I have been saying this and i
will continue saying this.
It's time for us to heal one
another, protect one another,
uplift one another.
I am outside every day a victim
of police brutality by myself
and my family.
>> thank you for your comments
.
All right.
Thank you for your comments.
>> so let's hear from our next
speaker.
You ready to go?
>> come on up.
>> I'm joel franco and I'm not
a resident here in san
francisco but I am a supporter
of the residents here in san
francisco and I'm here to
oppose the removal of max
carter overton.
I am here to stand by him.
>> and from what I'm hearing
from these people, he seemed to
be a man with good leadership,
great morals and values.
And I have to say though that
he's the kind of person that
the people here need and then
if you're going to remove
somebody, remove somebody who
keeps proving over and over
again that he chooses they
choose themselves over the
people and who keeps continuing
to say eh, the people don't
matter.
I do.
And also somebody who's
apparently too scared to take
accountability for their own
wrongdoings.
>> but max apparently is here
and he's going to continue to
be here.
So I will have to say don't
remove max at all.
>> please at least have the
decency see the courage and the
common sense to vote no and
stand against the things that
will continue to cause a lot of
harm so that communities here
from all walks of life.
>> that's all I have to say.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome to our next speaker
tonight.
>> so with my son I wish he was
my son.
>> sir, my name is frank noto.
I'm here on behalf of stop
crime action and our 4500
members.
And I am here to support the
removal of the commissioner
because his failure to serve
the public and to protect the
public safety san francisco has
a shortage of five 200 to 600
police officers.
>> and there's a reason for
that.
And that reason is partially
because of the attitude of the
police commission.
>> I don't question the
commissioner's intelligence or
his dedication.
But we need to have a police
commission that will enforce
the law fairly.
The commissioner failed to do
that when he required the san
francisco police department to
ignore california laws on
traffic safety.
We need accountability.
I also question his
independence and his
collaborative attitude.
He's not independent of special
interests.
He failed to engage with
citizens across the city,
especially on the on the west
side.
Again, we need accountability.
you have the legal authority to
remove him.
I urge you to do so and do the
right thing.
>> thank you.
I thank you for coming down
this afternoon.
>> let's hear from our next
speaker.
Welcome carolyn.
>> thank you.
Good afternoon, supervisors.
My name is carolyn goosen and I
work with the public defender's
office as their san francisco
policy director.
And in this capacity I've had
the honor of working closely
with commissioner carter over
stone over the past three years
on the policy to limit racially
biased stops.
>> and I wanted to come today
to share my support and
appreciation for his tireless
work to make our city safer for
all san franciscans.
>> he has not only provided
critical, unwavering oversight
of our city's armed police
force but he has also fought
for S.F. Pd to engage
in policing that does not rely
on racial bias and police
violence.
>> as you are all well aware
supervisors, we give enormous
power to the police.
They can as part of their legal
duties carry weapons, detain
people even children lie to
coerce information.
>> and they can even legally
take someone's life.
With this amount of power we
need to ensure that there's
strong independent civilian
oversight.
And this is what commissioner
carter stone exemplifies.
i've had a chance to witness
personally max's policing
policy expertise and his
measured, thoughtful style.
>> time and time again
everything he has done on this
commission he has done using
data research and is done
in collaboration with S.F. Pd
staff, with expert and with
diverse san franciscans.
>> as was mentioned, he led on
the most collaborative policy
process the commissioner the
commission has ever seen.
>> we are very fortunate to
have someone like commissioner
carter ober stone sit as a
volunteer commissioner in the
city.
And I hope you will allow him
to continue in this role.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome liam mcgeever hello.
>> so I woke up in 2020.
>> did you or were you just
faking it?
>> you know what I learned
in 2020 from the murder of
george floyd?
>> you always film the cops,
right?
>> I'm just going to film my
supervisor a little longer
because he's a big cop.
>> when you're being filmed,
when you're you know, having
someone look over your
shoulder, does that make you
feel a little different?
Like maybe you should behave a
little better.
>> we need that for the cops.
It is life and death and
there's a lot of death that
has gone on here.
And why aren't you interested
in stopping it?
>> I live in the heart of the
open air drug market.
I've lived there as a homeowner
for the past three years.
>> I have felt the ramp up of
policing in my neighborhood on
my front step.
>> and it's only gotten worse.
>> I am here to testify your
speedy answers don't work.
>> I want to defund the police
still I want to abolish the
police still okay.
>> I don't know what happens to
that sentiment.
It's only five years since
2020, right?
Was there a time machine?
>> are we like 100 years?
2020?
Like what the happened?
I'm glad people are realizing a
blue billionaire is just as
horrible as a red billionaire.
Okay.
There's no benevolent
billionaires.
Why does this billionaire ever
want to control us for a dollar
a year?
What is the rush to get rid of
police oversight?
I have seen what's happening on
six and ten.
>> thank you, leah and.
Thank you, leah.
Welcome to the next speaker.
As a frequent attendee of
police commission meetings I
have witnessed the commission's
operations firsthand and I have
often seen a routine pattern of
pushing personal agendas over
public will.
>> therefore I do support mayor
laurie's decision to remove
commissioner over stone.
Independence is good.
Oversight is necessary but
after sb 50 failed this
commissioners aggressive push
for digital 9.7 was right or
wrong.
In terms of pretext stops right
or wrong was his personal
crusade to implement
restrictions that both
california legislators and
voters have explicitly
rejected.
When state lawmakers declined
to enact something into law, it
is not appropriate for an
unelected commissioner to try
to force it through locally.
>> the city attorney's failure
to check these overreaches does
not make them legitimate.
It simply turns them into
costly litigation and future
ballot measures.
San francisco voters have
already attempted to course
correct this by voting
overwhelmingly by passing
proposition e because they
recognized how far the
commission's actions have
strayed from the parameters of
their charter commission over
stones removal is a crucial
step in realigning the police
commission with its intended
purpose by removing a
commissioner who consistently
pursued his personal agenda
over voter and legislative
intent.
This board acknowledges the
public's frustration with rogue
public officials and signals
its commitment to governing by
honest and democratic
principles.
>> when commissioners lose
sight of their role, disregard
voter will and attempt to
circumvent state law removal is
essential and appropriate.
It is incumbent upon this board
to do it.
removing max carter over stone
from his seat that he is using
for his own personal agenda and
I go to all the meetings is a
tremendous cause correction
towards public safety and
reestablishing trust in our
commission.
>> thank you.
I'd like the members of the
public please allow each
speaker to have their two
minutes please.
No interrupting.
Please.
Please proceed, ma'am.
>> hello?
Members of the board of
supervisors.
My name is angela chan.
I'm an assistant chief attorney
at the san francisco public
defender's office.
>> I'm also a former member of
the police commission.
Today you'll make a decision
that impacts public safety for
san franciscans.
>> no other entity in san
francisco has the same power as
law enforcement to build a
wield state violence to take
away your freedom and even your
life.
With that power I hope we can
all agree there has to be
rigorous independent oversight
by civilians to ensure that
police do not abuse it.
That is a system that san
francisco voters installed
decades ago and this is a
system that voters have
recently reaffirmed by
rejecting a ballot measure that
would have gutted this police
commission.
>> as a former member of the
commission who has seen the
inner workings of the police
department including the
serious and in some cases
violent misconduct committed by
some officers, I know what is
at stake.
We do not need more
commissioners.
>> commissioners who are former
or current prosecute ers who
are already too close to the
police to be independent.
>> we don't need more
commissioners who rubber stamp
and look the other way when
there's racial disparity,
misconduct and excessive force.
>> I've seen that too much on
the police commission but we
need our commissioners like max
carter overton who who's unlike
any mayor appointee I've ever
met and I mean that I've met a
lot.
>> he provides painstaking,
unbiased and thoughtful
oversight.
He deeply cares about community
safety and ensuring that police
are not disproportionately
stopping and traumatizing black
and brown communities.
>> he's a subject matter
expert.
There are not that many subject
matter experts I've seen on
this commission who's worked on
police reform prior to joining
the commission and most
importantly he is not afraid to
speak truth to power.
He's not afraid to whistle
blowing.
He knows something is wrong and
something is unjust with black
and brown lives on the line her
the most vulnerable, the
policeman's conduct we need
more serious smart and caring
commissioners like carter over
stone.
you heard his story.
He does this from his heart.
>> yeah.
Thank you.
Dedication.
I urge you to try to do the
right thing and save filner.
>> it's hard to know.
Thank you for your comments.
>> all right.
We're asking you to hold your
applause, everyone.
Next speaker, please.
Supervisors.
My name is zach dillon.
I'm a policy analyst for public
defender's office.
And I worry your minds are
already made up.
So most of my comments are to
be addressed to the people who
came out in support today.
>> I want to thank everyone for
coming out and supporting.
>> I think it's important not
only to show our support to the
work that max did while he was
a commissioner and while he has
been a question and hopefully
will continue to be a
commissioner but to anyone
who's appointed to this
commission the future should
also know that the community
members and advocates will have
their back and will support
them when they're doing the
work that needs to get done.
>> max didn't always do what I
wanted him to do.
I have a public defenders lens
on things just as I know he
didn't always do what the chief
of police or former mayor
wanted but he always explained
his thinking publicly and got
consensus on the commission for
some pretty contentious issues
.
The pretext policy he
shepherded along did not
include everything I advocated
for in the working group
meetings.
It didn't even include
everything from the first
published draft.
>> but the compromise he
reached was based on the
information available and it is
why it ended up passing
unanimously from the commission
and with the support of more
than 100 organization in the
city.
>> I do worry about the future
of the department without the
doj oversight and now with the
threat of losing a key voice
asking questions and probing
the edges of policies, will we
return to an era of police
setting their own policy on car
chases, police shootings,
racial profiling no knock
warrants at times going to have
to tell.
>> I was hoping that the mayor
would actually reappoint max to
a new term next APRIL which
whether he wants that or not I
don't know.
But if he doesn't, this board
should appoint max to a term.
The next time a commissioner's
seat comes up from this board.
>> thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Hold your applause, everyone
please.
>> next speaker.
Hello, board.
My name is griffin lee d2
resident and I'm here to
support their larry and the
removal and firing of max
carter over stone master as a
leader to the 9.07 which
limited our ability meaning the
police department's ability to
to do traffic enforcement since
diego 9.7 was accepted and if
negatively affected morale of
the police department because
it's another dojo to think
about when they're behind a car
that MAY have expired tags no
front license plate and stuff
of that nature in my and their
observation and this is coming
from a police officer I met
yesterday because of this
confusion.
Cops do way less traffic
enforcement which led to more
unsafe driving from the general
public.
Additionally, the acceptance of
the dijo has discouraged
proactive police work meaning
there is less traffic stop
traffic for someone over and
sees guns and drugs that are
killing us on our streets today
and people with arrest warrants
and cool stuff like that.
>> again I'm in support of
mayor lori and I highly
encourage you to vote on the
removal of max carter over
stone thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Nick speaker please.
>> hi, my name is brad chapman.
I'm one of the vice presidents
of the harvey milk democratic
club.
I want to thank supervisor
fielder and melgar for your
courage and I'm really feeling
anxious about this because I
know some folks on this board
and I don't really like to put
myself out there when I was
reading I mean I do I've done
it too much in the past and I
kind of want to get away from
that.
But when I was reading this to
my boyfriend he was like do you
want to put a target on your
back?
>> and here I go.
So here's some quotes.
A system that rewards
corruption that's what we have.
It's time to turn the page on
corruption in san francisco.
Our residents and taxpayers
deserve accountable effective
leadership.
No more backroom deals,
conflicts of interests or
broken promises.
We cannot continue to do the
things the same way they've
been done because we're going
to get the same results.
You can't solve the problem
when you are part of the
problem.
>> those are all daniel lurie
we all know we all know that
this vote is at its core about
taking power from someone who
put truth to power by a board
that is afraid to hold its
mayor accountable after so many
bridges were burnt with the
last one.
We all know that most of our
supervisors made up their minds
about how they'll vote on this
hearing before they heard us
speak today.
Are you going to be a part of
the problem or are you going to
be a part of the solution and
do our voices matter when
politicians and leaders
oversimplify, deny or exploit
public health crises?
Dorsey in the name of public
safety for personal gain
everyone loses.
You're a former spokesman
in dorsey for a police
department protected by the
power that unlimited power and
absolute immunity for police
officers should you recuse
yourself from this for comments
to the board as a whole as
well?
Okay.
Well harry to those folks on
this board who knew him
believed that tepid liberalism
kept those who are powerful
satisfied with the status quo
and that none of us should rest
until there is a fundamental
transfer of that power to and
people power and thank you
thank you for your comments.
>> if you'd like to provide is
a copy of that we can include
it in the minutes.
>> welcome to the next speaker
.
>> good afternoon everybody.
My name is justice doom la.
I'm here on behalf of treatment
on demand and safer inside
coalitions.
I'm here to ensure that you all
here once again MARCH quarter
over sound deserves to stay and
finish this term on the police
commission.
>> I don't think I need to
reiterate all of his incredible
accomplishments and attitude
and work that he does on the
commission.
>> but might I remind you all
that most of you voted to give
more power to the mayor?
And it seems like you're ready
to hand over yet again more
power to this new mayor who has
little to no bureaucratic
experience.
And so I just want to warn you
all that you have a job to do.
And I hope that you continue to
do that.
Weakening the police commission
is not going to help us solve
any of the other issues in san
francisco.
We cannot arrest our way out of
an overdose epidemic.
>> please keep max carter over
soon on the police commission.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker.
>> thank you.
My name is tyler.
>> I live in district five.
I usually hate to compare
people to donald trump.
I think it's kind of easy and
lazy but like let's look at
what's happening, right?
We have an executive trying to
get rid of someone who's in a
key oversight role.
He hasn't even really given a
reason as far as I know.
Is anyone here from the mayor's
office?
I don't think so.
Right.
He's not come to this meeting
or sent someone to this meeting
to justify this.
And he's acting like we should
just go along with it and that
the board should just go along
with it and just let him do it
without asking any questions
and he's acting like it's his
commission, that it's the
mayors police commission.
It's not it's supposed to be an
independent commission as
commissioner cartier-bresson
said at the beginning.
>> so you tell me if the
comparison with trump makes
sense.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker welcome.
>> thank you.
Good afternoon.
Board of supervisors.
My name is brian cox and I'm
here with the public defender's
office.
S.F. Has a long documented
history of sidelining and
silencing outspoken critics of
the police whether they are
outspoken policy advocates and
those within the department
itself or outspoken
commissioners like max.
Outside legacy continues today
with this sham vote to remove
him.
As I wrote in my letter last
week opposing his removal, max
is eminently qualified to
continue his work at the
commission.
Not only does he deserve to
finish this term but he
deserves another term.
>> his resume is seriously
impressive.
His credentials are impeccable
and his worth work ethic is
relentless.
No one has advanced any
arguments in public to remove
him only baseless speculation
and obeisance supports this
vote and that it is directed at
a black commissioner during
black history month is a stain
on this spine institution.
Shame.
>> in his role max has relied
on best practices, research
data, community input and
feedback from officers to form
his opinions.
That's what we want in a
commissioner and his list of
accomplishments in his short
term or seriously impressive.
And as others have noted I
won't go through them again.
But what strikes me as obvious
is that he has been consistent
and calling out the department
when it overstepped its bounds.
that's accountability.
That's the job.
And that's what he has done.
His northstar has always been
about asking the hard
questions.
The others are too afraid or
too comfortable to ask.
He's always followed his
conscience and we need that.
We need that from not just him
but from every other
commissioner to hold the
department and its officers
accountable.
Make no mistake what's at
stake.
This vote is really about the
future of police accountability
and transparency and oversight
in san francisco.
Every action that happens that
weakens transparency and
accountability and
accountability moving forward
because of this vote you'll
have to live with that.
>> thank you ryan dodson for
your comments.
Next week please and afternoon
supervisors.
My name is tess wellborn.
>> district five.
I'd like to address I'd like to
address two points.
>> the police commission
doesn't control the police
department.
>> if their closure rate is one
of the lowest in the nation,
almost every police department
across the nation is short of
officers.
Maybe it's time to think about
some other approaches.
>> I think that we are just
incredibly lucky to have
someone who with the expertise
of carter over stone and I
would think that we have to
keep him.
Let's see if you think that it
is good to replace somebody for
no good reason that has been
given.
No malfeasance.
No other crime.
>> no crime.
I'd like you to think about the
the parallels with trump.
Yes, but I'd also like you to
think about okay, who will be
next?
Who else will the mayor say?
Well, you were elected for a
term but forget that.
>> so what's the point of
having terms?
>> completely.
It's time to say that whatever
happens now could be a
precedent for future mayors
future and as well as the
current mayor.
And I think we've got to follow
a little bit of the rule of law
here.
You know, just a tiny bit and
keep this great man.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker.
>> good afternoon, san
francisco.
My name is starchild.
I'm chair of the libertarian
party of san francisco and here
on behalf of our over 3000
registered libertarians in san
francisco to support keeping
max carter over stone on the
police commission.
Libertarians strongly believe
in not only fiscal
responsibility and limited but
limited across the board civil
liberties vitally important.
I've been moved by many of the
comments here today and it does
just back my mind again and
again how just five years ago
in the wake of george floyd's
murder by police, people are
falling over themselves to talk
about police accountability and
the need to defund the police
and some people even talking
about the need to abolish the
police which are not part of
america's original heritage.
There were no police back
in the days of the founders and
we don't need an armed standing
army that they were concerned
about trying to control every
aspect of our lives.
And each one of you when you
pass laws you have to realize
what the law is.
It's basically an authorization
for those uniformed individuals
carrying guns to use as much
force as necessary to get
people to comply with it up to
and including shooting and
killing them if they resist.
So if you don't exercise proper
control over the police in your
oversight capacity including
keeping a strong police
commission which really should
be elected not appointed, you
will have blood on your hands
the next time there's a sheila
de toi or a mario woods or a
pat on gore or an alex nieto or
all the other victims of police
abuse and killing that if seen
here in our city.
And think about this and think
about executive overreach.
You see what's going on with
donald trump rallies san
francisco we have too much of a
strong mayor system where the
voters did say no to property
and there are limits and the
pendulum is going to swing
back.
And if you vote for his removal
today, many of you will be.
>> thank you, starchild.
Thank you.
Welcome to the next speaker.
>> hi.
My name is mario lemus.
I am a long term resident of
san francisco.
I took the afternoon off.
I hate politics.
I mean the backdoor dealings
and all that stuff is just
something I see a lot of people
glazing over here especially
shaman.
And you know for me as a
resident and marching in act up
in the 80s as a man to be here
this is unprecedented.
I mean it's it's kind of scary
to see that somebody is being
pushed out for no reason
whatsoever.
And for it seems like some of
you have already made up your
minds and taking a lot of
breaks and moving through.
And it's really terrible to see
it.
So you know, it it it's
disheartening to see so many
people coming here taking their
time off in in hopes that you
would keep max here to stay on
the commission.
I urge you to think think
properly because this is
dangerous.
It's going to be passed.
>> thank you for your comments
already.
>> decision.
Welcome back.
Former member of the board john
avalos good afternoon
supervisors as a member of the
board I actually rarely use
talking points but I need to be
more precise now this moment
demands real leadership that
unite san francisco for the
good of all not by imposing a
singular single point of view
and conditioning goodwill to
those of you who vote the right
way.
Leadership is doing the hard
work of building consensus
across differences.
True leadership means
assembling a team of rivals
practicing diplomacy and
governing the entire city not
just with the people who agree
with your point of view.
At the national level we face
an existential crisis.
Trump's executive orders amount
to a coup with mass firings of
federal workers and the
empowerment of public funds
being used to extort state and
local governments into
submission.
San francisco must decide
whether it will stand firm or
fall in line.
We will start practice the same
kind of leadership as
supervisors.
You are often forced into false
choices.
Sometimes it feels like a ton
of bricks hangs over your head.
But this vote is a voluntary
one and one that one.
It's not one of those town of
brick moments.
You shouldn't have to vote on
this at all if it is a forced
vote then our city has already
stumbled under new leadership.
Supervisors the public needs
the best of you.
We hope you can provide us with
transparency and operate with
the highest ethical standards
and not just toe the line of
what is acceptable.
If the mayor has truly shared
with you the reason he wishes
to remove mac's commissioner
max carter oberstar then and
you agree with it the public
deserves to hear it and
understand it.
If not, this vote will be seen
for what it is a course of
political act and stumbled
unaccountable leadership at a
time when compliance with the
federal means storing
immigrants and transgender
family members under the bus.
We should not be practicing
that kind of leadership in the
city of st francis.
I urge you to reject the
removal of congressional
commissioner carter oberstar
oberstar.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments
,MR. Toronto.
>> hi.
Good afternoon, MR. Barry
toronto.
I came here on another matter
but I felt after watching
everything.
>> I'm concerned about the
precedent being setting here.
>> first the clerk's office
taught me how to say his name.
Max carter overtown.
So that took a while to figure
out.
So now you figure out that this
is a precedent you're setting
by by removing a commissioner
who is appointed to serve out a
term and hasn't committed a
crime and hasn't done anything
that that requires this type of
level of attention.
So you're bringing attention to
yourselves.
You're bringing attention to
the fact that that the that the
disenfranchized communities of
color and lower income
communities are not really
fairly represented in certain
city commissions.
And you've already given the
the mayor a lot of of of of
leeway and on certain topics
and certain areas to solve
certain problems.
>> so now you want to remove
somebody who actually feels
represented in judaism.
So the social justice aspect of
it is tikkun olam, tikkun olam.
Look it up and I feel that by
not by bye bye.
By accepting the mayor's
decision here you are actually
going the opposite of tikkun
olam and you are going to
create more turmoil and
in these communities by by
already the mayor bombarded by
the mayor's request at this
point I'm saying there there is
a request for you to appoint
alphonso felder to the to the
mta board and he's a good guy.
I worked with him when they
planned out that they have
traffic and transportation
around oracle park which was
which was pac bell at the time
.
He's a good guy.
But the thing is is that is
that is replacing a vacancy and
we're not replacing a vacancy
here.
We're letting someone serve out
their term who represents
people who don't feel
represented.
>> thank you.
Thank you barry for all right,
everyone hold your comments.
>> welcome.
>> good afternoon everyone.
My name is chemistry.
My office and I pretty much
consider myself resigned from
public speaking in public life
.
But I was at home in the middle
of a final exam and because I
love education and listening to
this meeting and I had to get
up and do a few things number
one just put on some different
clothes.
And number two, going print out
something and look up a date
NOVEMBER 5th, 2003 when the
citizens of san francisco
passed proposition eight the
police reform measure which
really targeted the idea that
the mayor could just remove
someone on the police
commission because somehow the
way they were deciding things
didn't go as supposedly planned
or the board of supervisors
could just remove someone from
a commission, particularly the
police commission without any
justification.
>> citizens of san francisco
for that reason they became so
such a big deal because there
was also this thing called
fajita gate.
You can go look that up and
there was also the thurgood
marshall police riot and I was
the ptsa PRESIDENT Of that high
school when that happened and
it was tragic and there are
many things that have been
tragic but we made certain that
we passed that so these kinds
of things wouldn't happen.
And I came to speak to you just
to remind you if you didn't
know that there is still an
audience for this city now so
somehow maybe you didn't read
it but it was specific.
>> so this couldn't happen.
And so if you're doing this it
goes against that ordinance
that exists here in san
francisco and I don't think you
want to do that not as duly
elected folks over the last
thing I did I didn't e thank
you, kim sheriff's office.
>> nice to see you.
Thank you.
>> welcome to our next speaker
.
Hi, isha humphrey.
I wasn't planning to speak
today but I felt compelled to
express my gratitude to
commissioner carter ober stone
for being a leader with such
principle and integrity.
I think that we have been lucky
to have someone with his
expertise who has been willing
to lend that to us to serve
this city.
He's been a pillar for civil
rights and the community and I
think it's very telling how
many people have come out today
to speak on behalf of the
commissioner.
I think that he's been an
excellent advocate for the
community and I'm grateful for
the opportunity to stand with
him.
I sincerely hope that this
board stands with him as well
and I urge you to vote no on
this motion.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome.
>> hello I'm from quadruple a
another of ac's army of
associates always hyphenated
american.
Has there been some
overstatements here?
Yes I.
I can't see how this voting to
sustain this would not be a
step towards losing chief scott
you've got to figure he's on a
pretty thin rope as it is and
you know I actually think maybe
you know I've been watching the
news a little bit and I
actually think this kind of
dynamic between public and bill
scott, you know, it could be a
good thing you got one of
them's a local guy and other
one was hired nationally you
know different races I think it
could be very dynamic and
depending on how long bill
scott's willing to put up with
it, you know, heck, you know, I
don't see bill scott as not
being a person willing to you
know, go with anything that's
rational and reasonable.
I just don't see it.
I think that a vote to sustain
this I can't see how it's not a
vote to get rid of bill scott
and I that's all about I want
to stay about overstatements
about the attempt to remove the
overturn the removal of
overtone thank you otto duffy
for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker I,
I just wanted to just introduce
myself.
>> my name's obama.
I was born and raised here
in the city.
I'm also on the sheriff's
oversight board.
I by no means am speaking on
behalf of that board.
Speaking specifically as a
citizen myself I think carolyn
gossip from the public
defender's office mentioned
this earlier about how
collaborative max overseeing
was and I just wanted to add to
that in support of him he came
along with the human rights
commission and the somewhat
community development center to
speak on behalf of to speak to
the pacific islander community
which is where I'm from and I
thought it was very helpful to
to kind of share out the
pretextual policy and I just
wanted to add my support on
behalf of keeping max on the
board to the commission.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments
before the next speaker you're
welcome to come up sir.
>> before you begin though,
just want to invite any other
members of the public who are
here to address this item the
consideration of the removal of
commissioner obra stone please
come on up if you're ready to
speak otherwise this MAY be our
last speaker welcome sir.
I am lord justice and I want to
give all praise and glory to my
creator oh I to like a few of
the last speakers were
compelled to speak.
It's evident that there are no
criminal charges.
There's no question of ethics
or professionalism or else will
be in a different venue so
people such as myself will dig
deeper and investigate to see
what is the root of this
problem and it also enables us
to see who's on law is payroll.
So with that being said, it's
been evident that you hold a
seat, you hold a position to
listen to the people we have
opened up and we have held a
long dialog.
We have said what we want, what
we desire and with evidence so
it is now up to you as our own
you to do what you ought to do.
You hold no alliance to no one
but the truth so let it be
done.
>> thank you sir, for your
comments.
MR. PRESIDENT and with with
that public comment is closed
and I will declare item 21 to
have been heard and filed and
now supervisor dorsey thank
you, PRESIDENT Mandolin
colleagues, I think it's
important to frame
dispassionately and accurately
what is before us in this
hearing because charter section
4.19 provides that members of
our police commission generally
serve at the pleasure of their
appointing authority.
In other words, they MAY be
removed without cause except
that mayoral appointments and
removals are also subject to
board approval.
Now this is very different from
the approximately two dozen for
cause commissions whose
appointees are genuinely
independent and by design
beyond the reach of their
appointing authorities once
they're appointed these for
cause appointees MAY only be
removed for official misconduct
and examples of those
commissions include the airport
commission, the board of
appeals, elections commission,
ethics commission, health
commission, mta board among
many others.
By my count there is about 23
for cause commissions.
The police commission is not
one of them.
>> the reason that distinction
is important is that it shows
that our city charter
thoughtfully contemplate dates
that some commissions are
intended to have independently
empowered appointees and some
other commissions including the
police commission are not
designed that way.
Police commissioners are
generally accountable to their
appointing authority and that
is by design.
The narrow role we play here
in this hearing is akin to an
advice and consent role.
It isn't necessary for us to
reach any factual conclusion or
to make any finding to consent
to the mayor's removal of his
own appointee or his
appointment for that matter.
And so for me it's a very
simple analysis that comes down
to whether we should honor the
committee necessary for the two
co-equal branches of our local
the legislative and the
executive to govern effectively
and well and that's especially
important at a time when we
frankly have more urgent
priority is facing our city
than this one.
We have a newly elected
executive and mayor lurie who
has earned the right to seek
his own appointment where their
authorized as they are here
absent some extraordinary
circumstance, some grievous
error that we are losing a once
in a generation talent the lone
bulwark against fascism itself
which I haven't seen there is
no legitimate basis I have seen
to dissent from the mayor's
removal here now I have worked
for various offices in city
hall for nearly 20 years and it
has been my observation that
most conscientious public
servants who are at will
employee appointees usually
offer to step aside voluntarily
when there's a new mayor and
yes to do the classy thing so
that other worthy san
franciscans MAY have their own
opportunity to serve our city.
So to the extent there's
anything unusual here, it's
that this appointee doesn't
want to step aside and that's
fine.
That's his right.
But neither does it cause me to
look favorably on his retention
.
>> now I assume I reflect the
perspective of all my
colleagues here when I express
my appreciation to MR. Carter
oberstar and for his service to
our city.
I thank him for his work on a
commission that is known for a
lot of hard work often
thankless and in fact I'm
writing legislation to expand
opportunities for rewards
in homicide cases based on the
resolution.
MR. Carter oberstar authored
and I applaud his good work.
>> there's certainly no hard
feelings intended for me but at
the end of the day I don't
believe this is about MR.
Carter over stone.
>> I believe it is about what
the city charter says about
mayoral authority over mayoral
appointments.
In my view mayor lurie has
earned by virtue of his
election the right to make an
appointment of his choosing
exactly as the city charter
intends for mayoral appointees
to this commission and I've
seen no rationale in this
hearing to dissent on that
removal.
neither do I think it's a bid
to remove chief bill scott who
I will say I do consider a once
in a generation talent and an
extraordinary leader who has
led our police department
through 21st century police
reforms that led the nation.
However, on item two I would
move that this board consent to
the mayor's removal of max
carter ober stone from the san
francisco police commission.
>> thank you supervisor dorsey
there is a motion to change the
motion to say confirm is there
a second seconded by sherril
supervisor fielder thank you,
PRESIDENT.
>> thank you commissioner
carter roberson for being here
today to PRESIDENT Gentleman
for allowing him to speak.
I also want to thank public
defender mino raja, everyone
who came out today to make your
voice heard.
>> take time off work to be
here, watch the meeting unfold
and drive all the way here to
be here.
Thank you to third street youth
center san francisco bicycle
coalition.
San francisco gray panthers as
a rising tenants as a tenants
union small business forward
the acp chapter san francisco
harvey milk lgbtq democratic
club league of women voters and
dozens of other committee
organization ones that come
from all corners of san
francisco and for riding us
in these past couple of weeks
it is absolute the right of the
mayor to put forward this
motion and it is also our right
to reject that.
>> public safety is among my
top priorities as district nine
supervisor representing mission
berlin portola because during
my two year campaign I talked
to thousands of constituents at
their doors a significant
proportion of whom talked about
wanting to feel safe walking to
school to work and just living
their daily lives that safety
was put at risk for a police
practice that commissioner
carter aubuchon had exactly
warned about and I was I'm
talking about the crash
involving a as a vehicle on
super bowl sunday.
I've said before in this
chamber that when I got the
call that six people were sent
to the hospital including a mom
and child, I didn't know what
scene I was going to arrive at
and I want to address the
misconception that pretext
stops prevent officers from
pursuing want to vehicles
pretext stops did not stop as
if pd from pursuing a wanted
vehicle for miles from stone's
town all the way to the mission
crashing specifically this
wanted car crashing into a
light pole at 20 for the
mission another car that was
parked and then eventually the
parklet I saw the video for
myself and I've said before it
is a miracle no one died
in this crash.
>> these people are my
constituents that were sent to
the hospital.
I've spoken with a couple of
them who want accountability
from us a pd as much as
accountable for the suspects.
San franciscans have been told
that if we abandon reform, if
we abandon independent
oversight and if we give law
enforcement complete control
over budgets, over how they use
force, how they profile
suspects, how they chase
vehicles, how they spend their
own time that everything
regarding public safety will be
solved and san franciscans have
essentially been sold the story
that an accountable police
force is an ineffective police
force and voters through their
rejection of prop f in NOVEMBER
and also prop d around
commissions resoundingly sent
the message that they want
accountability as much as they
want public safety.
>> an accountable police force
is one that is held to the
highest standards of
responsibility.
>> an accountable police force
is one that is responsible for
every dollar just as every
other department is made to
justify their expenses just as
every nonprofit is made to
justify their expenses, an
accountable police force is one
that uses resources wisely that
ensures officers are not
putting the public at do risk
due to their own burnout.
>> an accountable police force
is one that knows its community
members and makes meaningful
progress on doj reforms.
People coming up for public
comment have talked about the
various people that have died
at the hands of the pd alex
nieto.
>> luis can go to pat mario
woods so many more and we have
made tremendous progress in the
past handful of years on the
doj reforms under an
independent police commission,
an accountable police force.
>> I believe is possible and I
see glimmers of hope in a true
community oriented police force
every day in district nine.
>> I mention all this because
commissioner max carter
robertson and I both know that
his removal is bigger than him
and that his removal is going
to lend towards not just
in unaccountable and less
effective police force but also
a chilling effect on any
oversight whatsoever that will
ultimately put members of the
members of the public in danger
.
>> commissioner carter
robertson has been a steadfast
advocate for reforms and
oversight.
His leadership has been smart,
principled and moral.
>> his work revealing the
corrupt practices of the last
administration earned him a
national award.
>> it is not anti-police to
want oversight just as us
politicians have to report on
conflicts of interest just as
we have to report to the ethics
commission very regularly, it
is on a principle that trust is
earned and he represents the
kind of principled, uncorrupt
independent governance san
franciscans want and he should
be rewarded for his service not
punished.
>> and so I urge my colleagues
to vote against the removal of
commissioner carter over stone
and allow him to continue his
critical work to hold as a
party to the highest standards
of responsible and
accountability and serve the
public with the highest
standards of trust.
>> thank you.
Thank you supervisor I was
pleased fielder supervisor chan
thank you.
>> I first want to express my
gratitude to commissioner
mascara over stone for all your
work that you have done your
advocacy for police
accountability and advancing
racial equity has allowed us to
meet significant milestones on
critical reforms to our
policies on pretext stops,
excessive force and more.
And those are the policy that I
am in agreement with strongly.
So thank you, commissioner.
>> this is why it does pains me
greatly that we're here today.
San francisco is facing
unprecedented threats on many
front more than ever it means
that we have to work
strategically put aside our own
egos to ensure that we not only
protect the progress we have
made but contain the incredibly
important work to protect our
vulnerable and marginalized
communities.
>> I really do believe that
many of us especially right now
in this city hall are committed
to ensure that our police
department is held accountable
to the community and continue
to advance criminal justice but
to sustain like this meaningful
accountability in police
reform, I think we must
recognize that it does not
hinge on any one person but
collective work that all of us
have to do to push for
structural change an
independent one independent
commissioner does not equate to
an independent commission.
>> for the past few years I
think many of us have talked
about what can we do to make
not just our police commission
but really all our commission
to be independent and with
accountability and delivering
results for san franciscans.
>> we've been working on many
different legislations and
policy discussions including
one that I will be introducing
to really create a split
commission that allow the equal
appointments equal number of
point means from the executive
branch and legislative branch
to advance the work already
started by the proposition
eight commission reform so that
we can continue to build and
dependency to the san francisco
commission structure.
>> with that said again it's to
recognize that commission you
know we I'm just really
grateful for your work and for
the role that you have played
since you're a first term and
continuing into your second
term.
It is with great regret that we
are here and that it's we're
now questioning whether you are
able to finish out the
remaining of the one year.
But that does not mean the work
should stop I think hopefully
not for you and not for this
body and not for those that are
here in city hall.
So with that thank you so much,
commissioner and thank you
PRESIDENT Mendelsohn.
>> thank you supervisor chen
supervisor melgar, thank you to
all the members of the public
who took the time and made the
effort to provide public
comment today I do not believe
in removing commissioners or
supervisors before their term
is up when there has been no
malfeasance or illegal conduct.
>> I had a respectful
conversation with mayor lurie
yesterday and explained
in answer to his request for my
vote that his reasons for
introducing his motion this
motion that this georgetown
university and stanford law
school educated legal scholar
who clerked for two different
justices at the ninth circuit
court of appeals in at the U.S.
District court for the northern
district that mayor lurie's
reasons that commissioner
carter ober stone's manner has
been needlessly confrontational
and difficult to work with do
not rise to my standard for
removal and I will be voting
against it.
>> it is the same reason.
>> it is the same reason that I
have not supported and do not
currently support any recall
efforts without opining on the
assessment of commissioner
carter opus.
So it is difficult for our
mayor to work with.
I must point out that all of
our jobs in leadership here
in san francisco are in fact
characterized by having to deal
with different people that we
disagree with.
We all ran for these jobs and
knew that coming in the police
commission should be a place
for debate and a variety of
viewpoints should be allowed.
>> we live still thankfully
though at peril in a diverse
representative democracy in our
city has always prided itself
in doing this the best being
the first to move forward on
social justice moving through
our disagreements despite
controversy and disagreement,
sometimes even violent
disagreement.
>> and as a former planning
commissioner myself I would say
that you don't have to agree
with your colleagues all the
time but that doesn't mean that
they aren't adding something
valuable to the conversation
and that they don't represent
viewpoints that members of our
community have.
>> there is no question that
commissioner carter ober stone
was selected because he has the
background to be qualified to
serve.
In fact he is eminently
qualified and whether you agree
with his viewpoints or not he
has served with distinction.
The charter is clear the mayor
quote the mayor with the
consent of the board of
supervisors with the consent of
the board of supervisors MAY
remove a member.
The mayor has nominated the
board of supervisors MAY remove
a member of the rules that the
rules committee has nominated.
While I acknowledge that the
charter gives the mayor the
ability to do this if the
intention of the charter were
for commissioners to follow the
policy of the current mayor and
not the mayor who appointed
them or the appointing board
for that matter the terms of
the police commissioners would
be coterminous with their
appointing authority.
There are 429 days until APRIL
30th when commissioner roger
stone term expires.
we all as elected officials
have to live with restraints to
our power.
This is unprecedented and
unusual and I cannot put my
name in favor of this motion
and I have to say commissioner
carter over stone thank you
very much for your service to
our city.
Thank you.
Supervisor melgar we have an
amendment before us which is
made by supervisor dorsey and
seconded by supervisor sherril
to modify item 22 to provide
that the board will consent to
the mayor's removal of max
carter stone from the police
commission and on that motion
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
randleman my amendment I
supervisor melgar no melgar no
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chin chin I
supervise supervisor dorsey
dorsey I supervisor engardio
and engardio I and supervisor
fielder no fielder no there are
eight eyes and three nose with
supervisors melgar chan and
fielder voting no.
>> all right so the motion to
amend is approved and on the
motion as amended MADAM Oh I my
apologies MR. PRESIDENT.
Just to correct my vote there
were a supervisor chan said I
my apologies.
I recorded you as a no my
apologies but regardless
supervisor MR. PRESIDENT's
conclusion stands there are
nine eyes and two nos with
supervisors melgar and fielder
voting no supervisor melgar
forgive me PRESIDENT I think
some of us thought we were
voting on the motion not the
amendment.
So do you want to rescind the
vote on the or a motion to
rescind?
Does anyone need to okay.
>> no, I guess it doesn't
matter.
Okay.
Okay so the motion to amend is
approved and then on the motion
MADAM Clerk MADAM Clerk, can
you please call the roll on
item 22 as amended supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
mandolin hi randleman I
supervisor melgar no melgar no
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor walton walton eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor and engardio and
engardio I and supervisor
fielder no fielder no there are
nine eyes and two nose with
supervisors melgar and fielder
voting no and the motion and
the item passes as amended.
>> all right MADAM Clerk, I
believe that that takes us back
to item 16.
Okay.
Still public on the action item
16 is an ordinance to amend the
building administrative and
public works codes to remove
the local requirement for
existing buildings with a place
of public accommodation to have
all primary entries and paths
of travel into the building
accessible to persons with
disabilities or to receive a
determination of equivalent
facilitation, technical and
feasibility or unreasonable
hardship to affirm the square
determination and to make the
appropriate findings.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on this item on
item 16 supervisor mahmood
mahmood I on item 16 mahmood I
supervisor randleman I
mendelson I supervisor melgar I
melgar I supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor sherril sherril eyes
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chen I
supervisor chen chen I my
apologies it's very hard to
hear supervisor dorsey dorsey
eyes supervisor and gaudio and
gaudio I and supervisor fielder
fielder I there are 11 eyes.
>> all right without objection
this ordinance is passed on
first reading MADAM Clerk can
you please call item 17 and 18
together?
>> item 17 and 18 are two
resolutions that pertain to
liquor licenses.
Item 17 is a resolution that
determines that a person to
person premise to premise
transfer of a type 21 off sale
general beer wine and distilled
spirits liquor license to
dapper hill llc doing business
as dapper located at 1198
pacific avenue will serve the
public convenience item 18 is a
resolution that revises the
type of liquor license
referenced in resolution number
5 to 7 dash 24 from transfer to
an issuance and determines that
the issuance of this type 90 on
sale general music venue liquor
license to urban life inc doing
business as neck of the woods
located at 406 clements street
and to request that the
california department of
alcoholic beverage control
impose conditions on the
issuance of the license.
>> okay I think we can take
these items same house, same
call without objection these
resolutions are adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 19?
>> item 19 is a motion to
appoint sabrina hernandez burt
hill, liam devlin and gregory
michael hardiman.
Terms ending JANUARY 31st, 2027
to the golden gate bridge
highway and transportation
district board of directors.
I think we can take this item.
Same house, same call without
objection this motion is
approved.
>> MADAM Clerk can you please
call him to item 20?
This is a motion to approve the
mayor's nomination for the
appointment of W.E. Wilson
leone to the police commission
for a term ending APRIL 30th
2028.
And I think we can take this
item same house, same call
without objection the motion is
approved.
>> and then I think we can go
to our committee reports.
>> yes.
Items 23 and 24 were considered
by the land use and
transportation committee at a
regular meeting on monday
FEBRUARY 24th, 2025 at 1:30
P.M. And were forwarded as
committee reports.
Item 23 is an ordinance to
amend the planning code to
create an exception for certain
distilleries, wineries and
breweries to establish on sale
liquor establishments in the
bayview neighborhood commercial
district subject to a
conditional use authorization
to affirm the second
determination and to make the
appropriate findings.
>> all right.
I think we can take this item
same house, same call without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading and
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 24?
>> item 24 this is an ordinance
to amend the planning code to
establish the leland avenue
neighborhood commercial
district and to make various
technical amendments to
incorporate the ncd into the
planning code to amend the
zoning map to rezone all
parcels fronting leland avenue
between bayshore boulevard and
cora street from a small scale
neighborhood commercial
district to leland avenue and
cd to affirm the secret
determination and to make the
appropriate findings.
>> and we will take this item
same house, same call without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading MADAM
Clerk let's go to a roll call
supervisor mahmood first to
introduce new business.
>> thank you.
Clerk thank you, PRESIDENT
Colleagues san francisco
remains in the midst of a
deadly fentanyl crisis with 633
fatal overdoses reported
in 2024 down from 810 in 2020
three but far above
pre-pandemic levels.
>> fentanyl itself accounts for
approximately 80% of overdose
deaths in the recent years with
even trace amounts proving
fatal exacerbating public
health and safety concerns with
open air drug markets in san
francisco contributing to the
growing fentanyl crisis
resulting in overdoses, mass
shootings, reduced public
safety and lower quality of
life for residents.
>> the impact on our
communities is disheartening.
>> that's why today I'm
introducing a resolution with
co-sponsorship from supervisor
matt dorsey and PRESIDENT
Rafael randleman for the
implementation of a drug market
intervention or dmi strategy to
address our city's fentanyl
crisis.
>> I believe this is necessary
because what we are seeing
in our streets is not normal.
>> for too long our communities
have been told to just accept
an open air drug market outside
their doorstep as the new
normal.
>> but it's not normal for 3000
500 children and their families
who live in our neighborhood to
walk past drug dealers every
day.
And it's not normal for people
to suffer on our streets and be
exploited by dealers.
>> but this resolution calls
for the implementation of a
three step model based on a
drug market intervention
strategy a framework of
incapacitation deterrence,
prevention of open air drug
markets and partnership
contracting.
A professor of criminal justice
david kennedy, who pioneered
the program and expanded its
use during the obama
administration to curb violent
crime and drug traffic
trafficking nationwide.
>> in fact, demise rooted
in proven methodologies that
have successfully curbed open
air drug markets by nearly 50%
in the cities that has operated
in and is undergoing pilots
in other cities today professor
kennedy has spent his life
creating new strategies to stop
gun violence and close open air
drug markets often through non
carceral methods.
By contracting with david
kennedy we would essentially
contract a specialist to assess
the unique aspects of open air
drug markets in san francisco
to diagnose the problem and not
only prescribe a solution but
work with our city departments
on a path towards
implementation through the drug
market agency coordination
center.
>> we already have an
interagency task force which
brings S.F. Pd and dpw together
in a concerted effort to
address this ecosystem that
contributes to the markets and
in implementing dmi this
resolution would expand on
demak operations allowing for
us live pd to hold drug dealers
accountable while increasing
support for workforce and youth
development and strengthening
community based drug market
disruption initiatives.
And all of this gets back to
good governance because
residents often will say why
haven't we made progress on
this issue?
Why is it getting worse?
>> and it's not for lack of
effort because we have not been
we've tried.
We need to be working more
methodically and tailoring this
approach specifically to our
city and that's why this
approach we are pushing forward
it has unanimous support from
the department some chicago
democratic county central
committee including the speaker
emerita nancy pelosi who
endorsed this framework last
year.
And we're tackling an evolving
crisis that has gone on for too
long.
As a board we voted in favor of
the mayor's fentanyl emergency
ordinance and using the
fundraising abilities of his
office.
>> I believe this can be funded
without using our budgets.
>> so let me be clear this is a
national strategy to begin to
make progress on this crisis.
Dema has saved countless lives
across the city.
It's past time to bring it to
san francisco as well and I
wanted to acknowledge against
supervisor dorsey who has been
advocating for this
infrastructure and this
initiative for years and
excited to co-sponsor this with
him as well.
>> I'd also like to introduce
and in memoriam in memoriam an
adjournment for a betty MAY
cooke's colleagues asked that
we adjourn her memory who
passed away after nearly five
decades of shaping and serving
the fillmore and western
edition communities.
>> there was a beautiful
service held in community for
her this past weekend full of
love and appreciation from
those whose lives she touched
in speaking with her daughter
tanisha, it's evident that
betty lived fully in that her
spirit lives and through her
impact.
>> betty was born in 1940 three
in prichard, alabama and moved
to san francisco in 1951.
>> she's graduated mission high
school.
She met and married the love of
her life.
James cooks in 1964 and
together they raised four
children faith patrick, tanisha
and antonio building a family
grounded in love and resilience
in 19 76 betty opened jp beauty
boutique, a business that
became a cornerstone of the
fillmore for 48 years she kept
her doors open through economic
shifts and neighborhood
changes, remaining a steadfast
presence just last year her
contributions were officially
recognized when jp beauty
boutique was added to the san
francisco legacy business
registry ensuring her name and
impact would be enshrined
in our city's history.
Betty's influence extended far
beyond her business.
She was a mentor, a trailblazer
for black entrepreneurs and a
symbol of perseverance.
She touched countless lives
customers, employees and
community members alike thanks
to the efforts of brothers for
change and the broader
community, betty was able to
receive her flowers while she
was still with us.
>> she is survived by her
husband of 60 years james her
sister barbara, her children,
her grandchildren and an
extended family that goes
beyond blood ties.
her presence will be felt
in every stylist she inspired,
every customer she welcomed and
in the fillmore community she
helped preserve.
>> we extend our deepest
condolences to her family,
friends and all who were
touched by her kindness and
unwavering dedication.
San francisco has lost a giant
but her spirit remains woven
into the city's fabric.
>> rest in peace, betty cooks.
MAY your memory be a blessing.
>> thank you.
Supervisor mahmood supervisor
mendelson.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues, I have two
ordinances a drafting request,
a letter of inquiry and an
in memoriam.
>> so get out a book.
>> the first item is on the
open for business contracts
streamlining act of 2025 a sent
a set of sensible contract
reforms to simplify the city's
procurement processes reduce
the burden of contracting
regulations on small
businesses, nonprofits and the
city and encourage more
competition for city contracts.
The city and county of san
francisco contracts for many
necessary goods programs and
services from office supplies
to the installation of a new
subway line.
Contracts ranged from a few
thousand dollars to hundreds of
millions of dollars every
single city department engages
in contracting.
But the way we currently do
things is cumbersome, complex
and costly over time and for
good reasons.
san francisco has added
numerous contract related
ordinances that seek to use the
city's market participant
powers to advance various
social policy priorities.
Often these have come without
much or any consideration of
how the new requirements
interact with existing laws or
impact the efficiency of the
city's procurement process and
such such ordinances are rarely
if ever repealed or even
reviewed for effectiveness or
cost.
>> admit administrative code 12
x was an example and in some
ways a counterexample.
In 2016, in response to the
proliferation of laws in states
across the country that
discriminated against the lgbtq
community, the city enacted 12
acts which prohibited the city
from contracting with
businesses based in states with
such laws.
Between 2016 and 2023 the board
of supervisors and mayor
expanded the reach of 12 acts
to include businesses in states
with restrictive reproductive
rights and voting rights laws,
bringing the total number of
banned states to 30.
>> reports by the budget and
legislative analyst found that
the 12 x was creating
significant administrative
burdens for city departments
and reducing competition and
driving up costs for city
contracts without any
discernable impact on the
behavior of state legislatures
and bound states.
In 2023 we repealed 12 acts but
in the process it had become
clear to me that 12 x was just
the tip of the iceberg and that
our procurement processes could
benefit from additional pruning
.
In 2022 I submitted a letter of
inquiry to the city
administrator asking her office
to provide recommendations for
a more transparent, streamlined
and less costly procurement
process for low dollar
contracts to encourage greater
competition and support the
city's small businesses.
In MAY of 2024, city
administrator carmen chiu
released her report which found
the following one low dollar
contracts are subject to the
same contracting requirements
generally as higher value
contracts making executing a
$10,000 contract just as
difficult as executing a $10
million contract in the prior
five years the city had awarded
thousands of contracts for
$200,000 or less accounting for
59% of the city's contract
volume but only 1.8% of the
city's total contract spending
meant that city staff and
suppliers were spending
disproportionate time energy
and effort on a relatively
small share of the city's
spending.
>> third, the city's current
contracting processes and
requirements create a high
level of administrative burden
for both city staff and
suppliers, making it more
difficult for the city to serve
the public.
Fourth, the city's contract
requirements make doing
business with the city
confusing and cost prohibitive
for some suppliers and small
and local businesses and
nonprofits are especially
impacted by high barriers to
entry which can run counter to
the city's goals of local
investment and equitable
contracting.
And fifth, the complexity of
the city's contracting
processes MAY also be limiting
competition to provide the city
goods and services.
For example, in fiscal year
2023 nearly half the
solicitations that the office
of contract administration
issued received just a single
response or no response at all.
That's not a competitive
process designed to get us the
best product at the best price.
So the city administrator's
report made five recommendation
to help address these problems.
One of these challenges one
improve the informal
procurement process which
refers to procurements under
the city's minimum competitive
amount currently $230,000 but
reset every five years to
simplify the city's contract.
Standard contract terms and
conditions which are
significantly longer than those
in other city cities and
municipalities.
Three.
Amend the city's procurement
requirements, update and
reconcile inconsistencies
in processes thresholds and
triggers for standardized
future procurement legislation
.
And five increase
inter-departmental coordination
in contracting and align policy
and administrative processes
across departments so the open
for business contract
streamlining act of 2025 builds
on the recommendations of the
city administrators report to
begin lessening the burden of
contracting regulations on
small businesses.
Nonprofits and the city
encourage more equity and
competition for city contracts
and ensure improved service
delivery for san franciscans.
And when I say begin lessening
I mean that I hope and trust
that over the next several
years we will together find
many more opportunities to go
further than this legislation
to move our out of its own way
and to create more
opportunities for more
businesses and especially local
small businesses to compete for
our work.
This legislation would create a
model template to standardize
future contracting ordinances
require the city administrator
to review any new potential
ordinances that significantly
affect procurement processes.
Update out of section
out-of-date sections of the
municipal code repeal sections
of the municipal code that are
no longer in use or are
duplicative of state law and
standardize thresholds across a
number of sections of the code.
There's certainly more much
more to be done and I look
forward to working with you
colleagues to do it.
I want to thank the many people
that have worked hard on this
legislation and reform effort
over a couple of years.
That is first our city
administrator carmen chu and
her exceptional staff
especially sophie hayward.
Rachel zukerman say a corella
and angela yip as well as molly
peterson and on torn on the gov
ops team.
I want to thank our drafting
attorney gus schreiber and
thank the many departments and
stakeholders with whom we've
conferred along the way and
who've been generous in sharing
their time.
Finally I want to thank henry
de ruff and melanie matheson
in my office as well as our
choral fellow mave skelly for
all of their work.
And I want to thank my early
co-sponsors matt dorsey and
bilal mahmood.
>> all right.
The drafting request that I am
submitting to the city attorney
to raise the threshold for
board approval of acceptance
and expenditure of grants from
$100,000 to $1 million and and
the letter of inquiry I am
sending is to the comptroller
to request that he prepare and
provide within 90 days
suggested accounting protocols
and procedures to make this
change without compromising
necessary financial controls by
the comptroller's office.
Securing board approval of
grant accepted expense is time
consuming although at almost
invariably results in the
board's approval of the grant.
And while board oversight is
important for many functions of
city I do not believe our pre
review and approval of grants
less than $1 million is
necessary or desirable in most
cases there are excess grants
with local matching
requirements and grants
requiring new hires have
implications for our general
fund but for most grants under
$1 million the controllers
review should be enough.
I want to thank the department
of the environment and
specifically leo chief for
responding to what was
originally my request to help
us understand ways for the city
to more effectively and quickly
pull down federal environmental
grants.
Those were the days.
Thanks as well to sophie
hayward and the city
administrator's office
comptroller greg wagner and his
accounting team for their
initial feedback on this
proposal and henry trf and
melanie matheson again on my
team for their work on this
initiative.
>> the other ordinance I am
introducing today is an
ordinance is a law a measure,
an ordinance to provide relief
to scores of property owners
who were unwittingly and
through no fault of their own
swept up in the sad and sorry
saga of bernie curren and
rodrigo santos.
In JANUARY 2023 rodrigo santos
a building and construction
engineer who had done extensive
work in san francisco and
served on the city's building
inspection commission and city
college board of trustees was
found guilty of leading
multiple fraud schemes tax
evasion and providing falsified
documents to the federal bureau
of investigations.
Santos had defrauded his
clients, submitted false plans
to the department of building
inspection and worked beyond
the scope of his permits and
dozens more than that often
times.
>> he also stole money from his
clients by misrepresenting the
fees that were owed to gbi and
keeping the difference.
That same year former gbi
inspector bernie kern was found
guilty of accepting illegal
gratuities for personal gain
in connection with building
inspections he had performed on
those santos properties.
Santos had made payments to
current to approve illegal work
including unauthorized
demolitions and unpermitted
construction.
>> the convictions, however,
were not the end of the story
for the city or for the owners
of properties that santos and
curran had touched.
In MAY 2021, gbi had initiated
an internal review of
properties that were associated
with either man.
Gbi identified nearly 5500 such
properties to be audited.
The internal quality control
audit looked for evidence of
work done beyond the scope of a
permit, unpermitted work,
missing inspections and other
violations.
It was completed this past
JANUARY and the good news is
that no imminent life safety
hazards were found.
>> however, a roughly 2% of
audited profit properties were
found to have unauthorized work
that would need to be brought
up to current code
requirements.
Of course the vast majority of
these owners had purchased
their properties without
knowing that either santos or
kern had done and had been
involved in unpermitted
permitted work on them.
They had no way of knowing they
would be hit with notices of
violation requiring them to
undertake potentially costly
corrective work on the
properties that could require
payment of tens of thousands of
dollars in unanticipated
payment and architectural fees.
>> one owner learned that their
staircase was illegal and they
would have to and they had to
pay $21,000 to cover diva fees,
legal fees and the hiring of an
architect to draw up new
drawings and permits and secure
permit sets to rebuild the
staircase consistent with
current code requirements.
Another owner learned they had
to redo a driveway because it
was not permeable and renovate
their front doorway because
they did not have the right
transom.
A third owner learned that
their home had not gotten its
required permits and therefore
among other problems now
required a conditional use
permit to comply with my large
luxury home legislation.
That particular case cost this
poor owner more than $50,000
in planning permit and legal
fees.
The ordinance I'm introducing
will establish an amnesty
program that will waive local
planning code violations for
this discrete set of properties
that were subject to dba as
internal quality control audit
.
The legislation will further
waive fees that would otherwise
be required to remedy such
violations and will allow for
refunds to property owners who
have already paid such fees.
I want to thank the city staff
who worked with us on this
legislation.
They saw the problems in going
after these property owners and
were eager to help us find a
way to provide relief and
specifically I want to thank
director patrick reardon at
wbai as well as christine
gasper tate, hannah patrick
hannon and matthew green on
in his department liz waddy and
erin starr from planning austin
yang, rob coppola, kristen
jensen and peter million from
the city attorney's office and
calvin from my office.
And lastly colleagues I am
asking that we adjourn today's
memory today's meeting
in memory of joe chavez who
died on FEBRUARY 1st at the age
of 89.
Joe was born in redlands,
california in 1935.
At 18 he joined the navy after
tours in japan and the
philippines.
He was stationed at treasure
island, which is when his love
of san francisco began.
Joe later moved to san
francisco after leaving the
navy and put down roots in the
castro.
He was a founding partner of
castro village wine company, a
small boutique wine shop in the
in the heart of the castro
neighborhood.
Established in 1980 cv iwc
specialized in the sale of fine
californian wines.
Joe and his partner boyd swartz
envisioned the store as more
than just a business.
They wanted to create a
community space for and
lesbians in the castro.
Joe and boyd were part of the
lavender wave that swept
through eureka valley in the
1970s and 80s establishing the
castro as america's most
important neighborhood.
They repaired, rebuilt and
invested in properties and they
were known to be amazing
landlords.
Yes, good landlords are a thing
and joe and boyd were it.
Castro village wine company has
been featured in local and
national publications including
the san francisco bay times
wine enthusiast line S.F. Est
and the bay area reporter.
There they were known for
providing jobs, mentorship and
professional development
opportunities for women people
of color and individuals
interested in the wine and
spirits industry.
And in 2012 former mayor ed lee
declared MAY 12th castro
village wine company day.
Boyd predeceased joe 13 years
ago.
Joe was one of the very, very
good ones and I'm going to MISS
Running into him out about
in the neighborhood.
He always liked to chat about
political gossips and city hall
goings on.
Our deepest condolences go out
to joe's friends, family and
loved ones.
Rest in peace and power joe
chavez.
MAY your memory be a blessing
and the rest I submit.
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor melgar submit.
thank you.
Submit supervisor sartor.
>> submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor sherril colleagues.
Last week PRESIDENT Trump is
issued a ridiculous executive
order that targeted the
presidio for dramatic cuts and
I use the word dramatic because
that is all this is drama
reality tv style drama.
>> so in response I'm
introducing a resolution that
firmly opposes this so-called
executive order calls it out as
the political stunt that it is
and reaffirms the city and
county of san francisco support
for a crown jewel.
>> we need to clear some things
up.
The presidio trust is fully
statutory so an executive order
targeting non statutory
spending is nothing but hot air
to the 3000 residents of the
presidio.
Do not fear to the 108 formerly
homeless disabled veterans
living in the presidio do not
fear.
To the nonprofits and
businesses who by the way pay
rent to fund the presidio do
not fear to the seven million
people.
That's twice as many as
yellowstone from across the
economic spectrum who visit the
presidio every year.
Do not fear this order does not
threaten the operating budget
of the presidio because it is
fully funded by revenues
generated within the presidio.
The presidio is a model of
efficiency.
It is a shining example of
public private partnership s we
need more treasurers more
models like the presidio.
And make no mistake it is a
national treasure and it is a
crown jewel of district two.
And frankly this is a direct
result of the stewardship and
care delivered by the team the
executive team and the board
members of the presidio trust
which brought this park to
self-sufficiency almost a
decade before it was acquired
by federal law.
If only we had more examples of
things that reached their goals
a decade before it was
necessary.
Trump cannot erase the law.
This executive order is again
nothing but hot air.
His bluster amounts to nothing.
It just creates unnecessary
fear for the 3000 people who
live in the presidio and the
countless others who rely on
the park as a cherished public
space.
I hope to have all of your
support in opposing this
political theater and sending a
strong message to washington
that we will fight to ensure
that the presidio that we know
and love is not going anywhere
.
And should this PRESIDENT Act
up again, we will be here
standing strong to defend
against terrible wildly
misguided ideas.
>> additionally, I want to
thank you supervisor mahmud for
introducing the resolution to
urge the implementation of a
comprehensive drug market
intervention strategy.
Dmi establishes common sense
collaboration prioritizes
direct communication and
ensures our resources are being
effectively used to end the
scourge of fentanyl once and
for all.
Open air drug markets create a
perception of instability and
raise fear in our city.
And recently in our two
districts we have had to
address the challenges at
jefferson square park that have
left nearby residents feeling
deeply unsafe.
We have to focus on
continuously disrupting drug
markets and restoring order
in san francisco.
I'm glad to be a partner on
this issue and a co-sponsor to
this resolution.
The rest I submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor sheryl supervisor
walton thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I have a
resolution and two in memoriam.
First I'm introducing a
resolution to reaffirm san
francisco's commitment to our
local business enterprise
program.
We will also be hosting a rally
next tuesday, MARCH 4th at noon
with our lbi and labor
partners.
Our city's chapter 14 be local
business enterprise program is
all about keeping opportunities
local and making sure small
businesses especially those
owned by minorities and women
get a fair shot at city
contracts.
When we prioritize obies we're
not just supporting businesses.
We're creating jobs,
strengthening communities and
keeping money circulating
in our local economy.
These businesses are more
likely to hire san franciscans,
pay fair wages and contribute
to the city's unique character
by reaffirming our commitment
to the hlb program.
We're doubling down on economic
equity and making sure all of
our small businesses continue
to thrive and are not left
behind.
Beyond economic benefits, the
resolution highlights the
city's dedication to fair labor
standards and inclusive
partnerships.
We're trying to uphold the
principles of fair wages safe
working conditions and
workforce stability by
encouraging the use of project
labor agreements and supporting
union projects.
Additionally, we are urging
businesses seeking to work with
the city to collaborate with
local obies in order to foster
stronger partnerships that
contribute to sustainable and
community driven development.
This resolution reaffirms san
francisco's leadership
in championing equitable
opportunities and ensuring that
small businesses and minority
owned enterprises have
meaningful participation
in shaping the city's future.
I'd like to thank our obie
community and labor partners
for working with our office on
this.
>> my first in memoriam is for
MISS Jean alexander.
Jean alexander was a beloved
wife, sister, mother teacher,
coworker and friend.
Born on OCTOBER 31st, MISS
Alexander gained her wings on
FEBRUARY 8th, 2025, leaving
behind a legacy of love,
service and dedication.
MISS Alexander was a devoted
member of our lady of the laws
catholic church where she
shared her gifts through the
ministry of music as PRESIDENT
Of the choir and as a
enthusiastic minister providing
comfort and care to the sick
and shut in.
MISS Alexander dedicated over
30 years of her life to
teaching, educating and
nurturing children at sojourner
truth child care center and
beyond this point saving the
lives of countless young minds
and fostering a love of
learning.
Her unwavering commitment to
faith, education and community
upliftment made her a pillar of
strength, wisdom and kindness.
>> always offering support and
encouragement to those around
her.
MISS Alexander's motherly love
extended beyond her own family
as she nurtured, mentored and
uplifted those in need, leaving
a profound and lasting impact
on the bayview hunters point
community and beyond.
Her worth.
Her warmth, generosity and
ability to bring people
together created a sense of
family and belonging that will
be cherished by all who had the
privilege of knowing her.
This in memoriam is for MISS
Loretta as woodson a woman of
strength, resilience and
unwavering love.
>> born on AUGUST 9th, 1956
in san francisco, loretta was
the chairs daughter of eola
taylor and john wilcher.
She was raised in san francisco
alongside her siblings and
attended daniel webster
elementary every middle and
graduated from galileo high
school in 1974.
A woman of great faith.
Loretta was an active and
devoted member of double rock
baptist church for many years.
She played the piano in church
as a child, served at the
church secretary and was a
member of the usher board.
In 1982 she met oscar rickman
and together they welcomed a
beautiful daughter jamie.
Later in 1994 she met bob
harris and they were blessed
with a son sidney loretta.
His greatest joys in life was
being a mother and she devoted
herself wholeheartedly to her
children and granddaughter
regina love.
>> her love for GOD guided her
life and in 2002 she earned an
associate degree in theology
followed by a bachelor's degree
in biblical studies in 2004
from survivor ministries bible
college.
MISS Loretta honed his skills
as a legal secretary a career
that spanned over 30 years.
In 1996 she took a bold step
into entrepreneurship founding
wiltshire's word processing
service offering notary and
legal services to her
community.
Later she pursued another
passion by launching love shoe
boutique, a venture she hoped
to pass down to her children as
a legacy of success.
>> despite facing challenges,
loretta is resilient, shown
brightly.
She overcame addiction and
through faith and perseverance
completed the 12 step program
at grace center in APRIL of
1994.
This triumph was one of her
proudest accomplishments as it
allowed her to witness her
chance her mother to witness
her transformation be her
before her passing later that
year.
Loretta remained clean from
that moment on were never
ashamed of her journey.
She embraced it as her
testimony inspiring many with
her strength and determination
.
In her final years, loretta
found joy in working as a
security officer.
Her favorite workplace was the
chase center where she worked
at games, concerts and events.
Always bringing her vibrant
energy to every occasion.
Loretta is life was a testament
to resilience, faith and
unconditional love.
She will be deeply missed but
never forgotten.
Her spirit will continue to
shine through the lives of all
those she's touched.
>> the rest I submit thank you.
>> supervisor walton.
Supervisor chin thank you,
MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I'm
introducing an in memoriam for
MR. John horton, owner of san
francisco toyota a longtime
business.
John was born in san rafael
in california on APRIL 17th,
1952.
A graduate of san rafael high
school.
John attended san francisco
state where he was majoring
in business who had hopes of
one day becoming a corporate
attorney.
>> however, one afternoon
in 1971 john saw a three by
five card on a bulletin board
that said general help needed
at bob reynolds toyota.
>> john applied and was hired
to sweep floors, wash vehicles
and organize the dealership's
lot.
And in case you don't know
where does lott is.
It's on gary in on in district
one and it's a big lot.
John worked hard and discovered
he had a passion for cars, the
business and the customers.
He decided to take a pause from
school and pursue his passion
for the car business.
After years of working
together, he and MR. Bob
reynolds develop a father and
son relationship.
MR. Reynolds gave john an
opportunity of a lifetime to
own the dealership in 1987.
John purchased a business from
MR. Reynolds and changed the
dealership's name from bob
reynolds toyota to what we know
today as san francisco toyota.
As san francisco toyota began
to grow both in size and
business, john began offering
small sponsorship to local
charities and community
organizations and local schools
and all of them and most of
them were actually in the
richmond.
For john and his associates,
donating time to support the
community was essential and
throughout the years they have
supported an array of
organizations in the richmond
district and across san
francisco without ever being
asked and he's going to be
missed greatly because it's not
just about him and his business
but really about his commitment
to make san francisco and our
community and definitely to
richmond a better place.
He will be greatly missed and
the rest I submit.
>> thank you supervisor chan
supervisor chin submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor dorsey thank you.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues, I have two items to
introduce and one in memoriam.
First time today introducing
the recovery first ordinance
legislation that seeks to
provide a clear and unifying
policy directive for city
agencies and contractors whose
services relate to illicit drug
use or to mitigating its myriad
and deadly harms.
This straightforward policy
directive will provide as
follows that the cessation of
illicit drug use and attainment
of long term recovery from
substance use disorders shall
be the primary objective of the
city's drug policy.
Now in some ways this isn't
different from the current
approach of our department of
public health all drug
treatment program offers
in fact aim to help people stop
using illicit drugs.
But I have increasingly been
made aware of instances
in which some public health
contractors seem to be rowing
in a different direction and I
think that became particularly
clear to me at a sponsored
overdose prevention summit I
attended last month.
One unfortunate consequence of
approaches that too often seem
at cross-purposes with one
another is that it causes more
and more san franciscans to
lose confidence in our approach
to a drug crisis that is
costing far too many lives and
that is taking far too great a
toll on our city and its
neighborhoods until long term
recovery from addiction is
universally embraced as our
shared civic goal.
I fear that our overdose
prevention plans will be little
more than overdose postponement
plans.
I have been open
in acknowledging my own journey
and recovery from drug
addiction as my primary reason
for seeking this job and I
strongly believe that in much
the way that transit first
animated our city's
aspirational urban urbanist
vision five decades ago a
recovery first drug policy will
provide san francisco with a
clear and unifying north star.
We need for the new and unique
challenges we face in the era
of synthetic drugs like
fentanyl and methamphetamine.
Given the grim reality of
today's street drugs which are
more easily trafficked, more
profitable, more potently
addictive and deadlier than
ever before in human history, I
think it is time to put
recovery first.
And I'm grateful to the early
to my colleagues for the early
co-sponsorship of board
PRESIDENT Mandolin supervisors
mahmood sherril melgar and
guardiola and sadr.
And I look forward to having
more conversations with
colleagues and community
members to broaden support for
this ordinance.
Second relatedly, I am also
announcing a legislative
drafting request for an
ordinance that would govern
expenditures and accounting for
remaining opioid litigation
settlement dollars for the
duration of that fund's
existence.
The legislation would also
create reporting requirements
to keep this board and future
boards apprized of annual
expenditures.
And it would hopefully find
agreement for an approach that
I believe enjoys wide support
on this board of supervisors
for a four pillars drug policy
model.
Along the lines of that
implemented by our sister city
zurich, switzerland and several
other european cities.
And for those who haven't read
it, I would urge everyone to
read the a report commissioned
by our former colleague dean
preston on zurich's
implementation of this
promising approach.
The legislation I'm asking for
would require that remaining
dollars from the opioid
litigation settlement fund and
I believe we anticipate a total
recovery of at least $350
million for the city and its
taxpayers before 2040 be
apportioned into four
categories correspond with the
four pillars as as follows 25%
for prevention to educate at
risk populations on the deadly
risks of illicit drug use and
also to research known address
histories for drug involved
populations 25% for treatment
and recovery to support
individuals with substance use
disorders to access drug
treatment or medically assisted
therapy and meet for long term
recovery 25% for harm reduction
to support people who use drugs
to minimize risks associated
with illicit drug use while
supporting and incentivizing
them to make better and more
healthful choices.
And 25% for law enforcement and
repression to more effectively
mitigate public drug use and to
maximize the likelihood that
criminal justice interventions
for drug related lawlessness or
life saving interventions.
I welcome the opportunity to
work with colleagues on this
approach.
Once I have an initial draft
from the city attorney's office
and I hope to earn my
colleagues support.
>> finally at our last board
meeting we had only just
learned of the passing of
ethics.
Crowley and I as I mentioned at
the time of my brief request to
adjourn that meeting two weeks
ago in his honor.
I wanted the opportunity to
collaborate with his family and
friends, especially in the
labor community on an
in memoriam that would be
worthy of the man he was and
the lifetime of service he
provided to our city and to its
working families.
It's what the heavy heart to
offer words of remembrance to
somebody I considered a friend.
Ethics crowley was a man whose
impact on this city and its
people is impossible to
measure.
by all accounts he was more
than anything a man of
boundless love for his family,
for his friends, for the labor
movement and for all san
francisco.
He didn't just say he cared.
He showed it.
Before you could even ask how
he was doing he was already
asking about your family.
He was a devoted husband to
nancy, a loving father to
jillian, bob kerry and margaret
and a proud grandfather to
payton and soon to be grandson
xavier.
But his family extended far
beyond his home.
He was a friend, mentor and
trusted colleague to so many
in labor and civic communities.
A third generation san
franciscan effects grew up with
a deep love for his city.
He was a proud graduate of
saint ignatius college prep
where he was a starting varsity
linebacker and a two year
letterman for the wildcats.
He was a recipient of the J.B.
Murphy award an honor given to
the player who best exemplifies
the ignatian spirit through
inspirational leadership on and
off the field.
That spirit of leadership,
integrity and dedication
defined his life effects was a
lion of labor.
He spent his career fighting
for working people an
influential conscience for
dignity and fairness in every
negotiation.
And labor wasn't just his
life's work.
It was also in his blood.
His late father john f crowley
was the secretary and treasurer
of the san francisco labor
council, a revered figure
in the movement who shaped
policies that improved
countless lives.
His late brother john p crowley
was also part of that proud
tradition.
F x carried their rich labor
legacy forward with honor and
determination.
As head of I.R.S. Local 16 for
seven terms he gave me me my
first ever labor endorsement
when I was a ds triple c
candidate in 2012.
He would later serve as the
business agent for I.R.S. Local
119.
Through it all, his advocacy
secured prevailing wage
benefits for film and
theatrical workers an
achievement that continues to
uplift families today.
He served on the san francisco
labor council executive board
for more than 25 years, always
standing up for those who
needed him most.
He also brought people together
organizing catholic labor
breakfasts for two decades
bridging the social justice
tenets of the faith we both
shared with the labor movement
in ways only he could.
His leadership wasn't just
about negotiating contracts.
He was also about creating
opportunity.
F x played a key role
in crafting crafting film
incentive legislation helping
bring thousands of jobs to san
francisco and ensuring stable
careers for film, theater and
entertainment workers beyond
labor.
His dedication to public
service included serving on the
civil service support and
public utilities commissions
for more than 15 years for our
city.
Always leading with fairness
and integrity.
Ethics knew how to enjoy the
life he left far too soon.
His mornings at rocks cafe and
dog walks at stern grove bike
rides through golden gate park
with nancy vacations in tahoe.
He had a way of bringing people
together whether over a long
lunch or a lively phone call.
Always on speakerphone, of
course effects was full of
compassion.
Always willing to lend a hand
to find a friend or stand up
for what was right.
His integrity generosity and
unwavering support for those he
loved.
These are the things we'll MISS
Most.
You are missed.
Thanks for your legacy of
leadership friendship and
service will endure in all of
those whose lives you touched.
>> rest in power.
Ethics.
Crowley and the rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor dorsey supervisor
and engardio.
Submit.
Thank you.
And supervisor fielder.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues, as you all know, we
are facing a growing crisis
in san francisco.
The closure of retail
pharmacies across our city
pharmacies are not just a place
to pick up prescriptions.
They are vital health care hubs
that provide lifesaving
medications, vaccines and
essential health services.
Yet due to the relentless
pressures of corporate
consolidation declining and
slow reimbursement rates and
industry mismanagement, we have
seen pharmacy after pharmacy
shed stores leaving our most
vulnerable residents without
easy access to care.
>> local 50 pharmacies are
reported to have closed in san
francisco between 2015 and
JANUARY 2025 with 12 more
slated to close this month.
>> further deepening the
pharmacy access crisis.
Seniors low income families and
individuals with chronic health
conditions are disproportion
greatly impacted as
neighborhoods risk becoming
pharmacy deserts.
>> we cannot stand by while
access to essential medications
and services are stripped away
from our communities.
>> today I'll be requesting the
budget and legislative analysts
to complete a report of the
feasibility of adopting a
cooperative pharmacy model
in san francisco show
recommendations for local and
state policies that would
support independent and co-op
pharmacies and proposals for
the city to support existing
independent pharmacies.
>> we must explore innovative
solutions that prioritize
community health over corporate
profits and ensure that every
resident has access to the
medications and care they need.
>> as part of this initiative
we will also conduct a
comprehend sieve analysis that
will assess national and local
pharmacy closure trends
identifying neighborhoods most
affected.
Investigate the root causes of
these closures including the
role of pharmacy benefit
managers and industry
consolidation.
Examine what it would take
legally, operationally and
financially to establish
cooperative pharmacies in san
francisco.
>> explore successful models
from other cities that have
addressed pharmacy deserts.
>> consider how we can expand
pharmacy operations through our
department of public health and
community health clinics.
Recommend local and state
policies to support independent
and cooperative pharmacies.
>> evaluate strategies for the
city to negotiate lower drug
prices to make medications more
affordable.
Identify alternative revenue
streams to support pharmacy.
Sustainability.
>> highlight the critical
health care services that
pharmacies provide beyond
prescriptions.
That last point.
The goal of this report is to
develop tangible actions that
we can take to keep our many
independent pharmacies open and
accessible for all san
franciscans while also
proposing policy solutions that
could help us expand
independent pharmacies in the
future.
I look forward to working with
all of you to build a future
where every san franciscan no
matter where they live has
access to the health care they
deserve.
>> thank you.
The rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor fielder.
MR. PRESIDENT, seeing no names
on the roster that concludes
the introduction of new
business.
>> all right, let's go to
public comment.
All right.
Those of you who are here
in the chamber for general
public comment line up by the
windows on your right hand side
of the chamber.
>> you MAY speak to the minutes
as presented general matters
not on today's agenda but must
be within the board subject
matter jurisdiction.
>> all other agenda content
will have been reported out to
the board by an appropriate
committee where public comment
has already occurred.
And for those of you who are
in line I just want to make a
quick comment that the
committee of the whole the
removal of max carter over
stone from the police
commission has already had its
public comment.
So you MAY not speak to that
item during general public
comment for speaker yes, not
too early on.
>> no matter how hard you try
you can sidetrack me you
because you no matter how hard
you try you can't either.
>> you know the distribution of
the roads is okay.
>> you're going to do this.
You're going to use vaccines to
kill people and that's it.
So that's why I said injections
are not allowed by this case as
long as you won't address the
problem of weather manipulation
which mess with the skies you
are done.
>> you are fake representing a
fake which is sooner or later
it's going to force me to
disobey systematically anything
that the asks you to do
including on the roads you see
oh yeah you can stop.
>> you for you know of course
no absolute incompetence.
Good air sea technology lowers
your intelligence to a level
that you can't get out of the
trap.
>> we said no qr codes, no cell
phones.
It's time bombs.
See, there is an attack coming
up.
I said you have to protect
yourself if you want to be
alive by JULY you don't listen.
Two years ago on the 28th of
FEBRUARY 2023 I said I'm
changing the course of humanity
under the order from the skies
to do it.
>> do you think I was that
sure?
>> do you think you're going to
get away from it?
I just it's an order.
I will do it.
I don't know you wait the more
I get out of control
understanding how to do it
everything is perfectly
orchestrated by this guy's.
>> I guarantee you that that's
what you so last but not least,
what is it next time you tired
me today big time.
But I'm coming back.
Of course.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome.
next speaker it evening I'm
here concerning my son I am
very disappointed and I know
we're not speaking on it but
I'm hoping that the resolution
that he made going to be
passed and I use the overhead
the resolution that max carter
of wisdom I implement it for
unsolved homicides.
I know matt darcy is going to
help with that.
Right.
Please.
I bring this with me because it
says that former mayor gavin
newsom he said I know who
killed her son.
Did gavin newsom said the D.A.
No, the police know.
If you know all of this, why
isn't our cases solved?
I have nothing against them.
But this was a slap in the face
and I still look at it today I
pray I mean for someone to say
they know I'm not nothing
against him but that's showing
that people know who killed my
son but they say what no
witnesses quote unquote no
witnesses.
I carry my pictures with me
every day for this is what the
perpetrators left me and people
that are helping us are being
taken away from us.
Our children.
>> I have to fight for my child
a child again, it's almost like
killing him again over and over
again I keep having to fight
and I'm asking for you
supervisors to to think about
unsolved homicides.
Thank you, MS..
>> brown.
Please ask thank you.
Next speaker please.
>> my name is marcello fonseca.
i am a career cab driver prop a
of 2007 which gave the mta
plenary power over taxi related
matters were sold to the taxi
industry as a promise of
reform.
>> our mayor back then
mentioned that in his quest to
monetize taxi permits he
mentioned that taxi medallions
had been underutilized and the
taxi industry had
underperformed.
Ironically what we have today
is a crisis.
We have a dysfunctional
medallion sales program.
We have a broken medallion
system.
We have hundreds of medallion
buyers.
The real victims of the failed
medallion sales program
drowning in debt.
They are driving themselves to
their graves with no future
prospects.
We also have the aging
population of medallion holders
who acquired their permits
under prior rules who are being
relentlessly targeted by the
mta just because they can no
longer drive the george
horrible a medallion holder who
drove full time for 43 years
had he went through seven
hearings before the mta was
finally successful in revoking
his medallion after sitting
here for five hours to speak
now I understand that this
medallion crisis is not the
only problem sen francisco is
faced with but it is a san
francisco problem.
I'm here to ask you to remind
you that it requires the
political will of the city of
san francisco to resolve this.
maybe you could form a
committee to address this
matter, work with the mayor's
office and direct the mta to do
a better job.
>> this has been going on for
too long.
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> thank you so much for your
comments.
Next speaker please.
>> good evening.
My name is nunley sharma.
I am speaking on the behalf
opportunistic smallholders
driving taxi cab is on this job
you concern about section eight
disable these homeless people's
you never concern about us and
you told us when we this
medallion we will have a better
day tomorrow.
We never had that we do not
want to live in tomorrow we
want to live in today at a
peace use rideshare killing us
our life is terrible.
We are suffering.
We know you are enjoying it pun
tastic life you are not
suffering.
You do not understand our
english we repeat again and
again our issue you do not
understand it.
>> I don't know what kind of
english you want us to speak.
Our business is dead because of
incompetent administer
administer of empty you you
should terminate incompetent
employees of mta we requested
you many times we lost over
everything new york city fix
the taxi medallion they lower
the price on medallion from 1
million to $200,000 we want to
lower the price on medallion
from $250,000 to 150 $125,000
because mta sold 200 medallion
with that price ten years ago.
The mta is using the taxi
ticket against us.
>> we never ask about free ramp
taxi medallions.
We never ask us for free any
>> so please concerned our
issue and solemn of our issue
reduce the price on madani to
$125,000.
>> thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker my name is ali.
I'm the same medallion problems
and you guys know all these
things so I want to tell you my
pain.
This pain has been growing day
in and day out for more than a
decade.
Nobody feel that pain because
only the person who go through
that pain who feels that pain
and we've been feeling that
pain for years how many people
assassinated?
How many people have a heart
attack?
How many people have a stroke
and we're still holding on
hoping that hopefully they'll
fix that problem.
But if you feel that pain then
you will fix that.
But every other step can do it.
Why can you not do that?
But I just say I'm not a mean
person.
I'm not a bad person but I will
say my lord as much as pain
we've been getting from the
people who are accountable for
that just not more and not a
lot, not less they should get
the same pain we've been going
through so then they will feel
it and then they'll fix it if
they fix the problem then i
will say GOD relieve the pain
of them because they felt our
pain and fix our problem.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker thank you
supervisors mark gruber with
the san francisco taxi workers
alliance.
I imagine that most people
in this room are appalled at
what's going on in washington
and across the country.
Among other things, the trump
administration has declared war
on some of the most powerless
and vulnerable among us our
immigrant population.
What distinguishes places like
san francisco from the get rid
of the mall crowd is support
for their struggles, respect
for their humanity.
And yet despite all his
professed values, san francisco
has betrayed and abandoned an
immigrant population right here
in its midst.
San francisco taxi drivers it
betrayed them by luring
hundreds of them into
purchasing taxi medallions that
previously were earned through
experience and again by
allowing uber and lyft to
operate illegally and yet again
by failing to fix the broken
system it created not a single
taxi medallion has sold for
nine years.
In the meantime, 40% of these
drivers have lost their
medallions to foreclosure for
the ones that are left the
prisoners in the system the
only way out for them at this
point is default or death.
>> the mta and the san
francisco federal credit union
are supposedly negotiating a
solution to this debacle but
it's been dragging on for years
and the people with the most to
lose the medallion holders have
no seat at the table who will
look out for their interests
while the mta is looking out
for its own.
It's a classic conflict of
interest.
This program has failed long
ago.
The mta has made $63 million on
medallion sales and their
self-interest in any resolution
is self-evident this board
needs to step in.
You have power over the mta's
budget.
You have power if need be to
put this before the voters and
you have the power and in my
view the obligation to right
this wrong.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
Yeah hi.
I just saw my colleague speak
about this city.
This is not a city this is not
a liberal city.
It's a cruel and callous city
who preys on its weak and
vulnerable because they cannot
fight back.
>> we have been coming here for
15 years has denied anything
being done.
>> no, because I don't have
lots of money.
I don't have 500 people behind
me.
You only work for somebody who
has a lot of clout among
themselves.
And one thing this gentleman
was set free and not ten times
about lambert street.
Lambert what is happening over
there?
Can you guys say something for
the cab drivers?
Do not fear we are with you but
I know it won't happen.
It will not happen simply
because uber, venmo and others
they are more powerful and they
have much more money to spend.
I am not seeing what you think
I'm saying but I'm just
speaking my mind.
This is what I feel people have
a right but you can't just sit
there.
I know there are a lot of new
supervisors they do not know
what's going on but I want to
tell them have a heart, have
mercy.
You have to sleep just like I
sleep at night.
Do you sleep peacefully?
I want you to sleep peacefully.
>> bring the price down to one
25,000.
Why?
Because most of the drivers the
medallion owners have already
paid that by might amount.
>> take my medallion sell it.
They'll be so many buyers young
kids who want to buy it.
But again will you work on it?
GOD knows only I can pray and
across the providence that some
sense goes into your head that
you think about the vulnerable
and the who cannot fight back.
Some day this will happen.
>> let's see sooner than later.
Thank you.
Thank you so much for your
comments.
>> next speaker hi.
So I came here to talk about my
supervisors new legislation
recovery housing.
I made a public comment this
afternoon and an associate of
my supervisor who goes by J.J.
Smith has already posted my
comments to rile up hate
agaie.
>> so let's just go through it
together.
>> here we go.
I'm not biased.
I just don't know he she it
wants to defund the police
because they're cleaning the
neighborhood up and protecting
its property.
Todd davis says would you you
would think if you knew you
were being filmed you might not
cuss like a drunken sailor.
Tom wolf the screamer is back.
>> adam resnick, who is a
member aboard a board member of
this on the west dvd that you
just congratulated today says
lunatic was were is probably
the proper pronoun so I can
smell it through my phone.
Mental illness is the new norm.
>> someone send that piece of
to another country.
Um let's see what what's see
bring back the mental asylums
which I believe this board is
trying to do.
Um let's go back to this one
because we have gina saying hit
the scream I don't know with
you know, physically hit me.
>> I don't know what gina of
mothers against drug addiction
and deaths you know there are
very involved in policy here as
well.
>> I just want you to recognize
how dangerous this is as a
trans person, a latin next
person in this country even
in san francisco this is called
stochastic terrorism.
>> I keep telling you that you
keep supporting this man and
his psycho bullies who harass
me for wanting to help homeless
people.
>> what the?
>> next speaker, please.
Dangerous man good evening, san
francisco starchild chair of
the libertarian party of san
francisco lp asphaug I just
like to remind folks and this
is maybe more to those watching
on tv or listening or you know
who knows reading this
listening to this in the future
then for the politicians
sitting here because I know
your minds and your careers are
pretty fixed but a lot of
things does can be better
understood if you think of it
as a for profit operation.
I call governments super
corporations.
You know they have all the the
greed, the self-serving, the
institutional dysfunction, the
bureaucracy uncaring of big
corporations.
But on top of that they have
armed gangs of police and
people to enforce their will on
the public non consensually and
all the money that they have
all the money that they get
almost without exception a few
voluntary donations but most of
it is obtained non consensually
basically it's a large criminal
gang and most of what is being
done is also illegal
unconstitutional which is a
fancy word for illegal.
The people carrying it out are
in fact criminals for example
the war on drugs no
constitutional authorization
from 1919 to 1933 this country
had alcohol prohibition that
was voted on in the
constitutional amendment.
There's been no amendment
outlawing marijuana, cocaine,
any other so-called banned drug
.
>> so the people out on the
streets persecuting people for
selling these things and
putting them into their own
bodies arbitrarily consensually
are the criminals the people
criminalizing use of public
space, criminalizing poverty,
trying to sweep people off the
streets who are there because
they don't have housing because
of the policies the has put
in trying to extort money from
people.
It's like they extorted money
for the taxi drivers that we
heard from earlier.
If you have a car you should be
able to drive your car and
charge people for rides without
paying extortion peace.
So the should be able to use
rooms in your house without
paying extortion fees.
>> thank you for your comments
.
It's been a while.
Next speaker please.
>> hi, my name is kim.
I'm one of the owner of the
medallion which is abused by
the sister of the the city of
san francisco and I know you
guys can do something change
and you guys should allow us to
make a negotiate or discuss a
meeting or something like that
and do you understand and and I
believe that you have
responsibility for this issues
of the medallion sales you all
know that but you just don't do
that since I don't want to